<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Applications Overview" target="ApplicationOverview">

	<introduction>
	Applications allow users to define the quantitative conditions needed to define, 
	run and visualize a Virtual Experiment, i.e. a numerical simulation of the BioModel 
	with specific initial conditions, within a given geometry, and with a selected type 
	of simulation method. In the Application,
	<list> 
	<item>the mapping between the model and the geometry 
	is established in the <link target="GeometryOverview">Geometry</link> tab</item>
	<item><link target="SpecificationsOverview"> Specifications</link> for species, reactions and network 
	(for rule-based application) are defined,</item> 
	<item>specific <link target="ProtocolsOverview"> Protocols</link> 
	(events, electric stimulation) can be included,</item> 
	<item>for each application, multiple <link target="simulations_overview">Simulations</link> 
	can be created that can include different initial conditions.
	</item>
	<item><link target="PEOverview"> Parameter Estimation</link> can be performed</item> 
	</list>  
	</introduction>

	<appearance>  
	 Applications can be 
	 <list> 
	<item><def target="def_Deterministic">Deterministic</def></item>
	<item><def target="def_Stochastic">Stochastic</def></item>
	<item><def target="def_HybridDeterministicStochastic">Hybrid Deterministic Stochastic</def>, 
	a stochastic model with spatial geometry and at least 1 species specification set to 'Force Continuous' 
	(See <bold>Spatial Stochastic </bold> under <link target="SpeciesSpecifications">Species Specifications</link>).</item>
	<item><def target="def_RuleBased">Network-free</def>, a special single-compartment stochastic <link target="NFSimApp">network-free application</link> </item> 
	</list>
	<imgReference target = "ApplicationTypes.png"/>.
	<para> Additionally, by defining <link target="GeometryOverview">Geometry</link> deterministic, stochastic or network-free 
	applications can be made into </para>
	<list> 
	<item><bold>Compartmental</bold> (1D, 2D or 3D), where topology and size of compartments are defined, but species are assumed 
	to be well mixed within their compartments. Such application is simulated using either differential equations
	(for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> application), or using stochastic simulation algorithms 
	(for <def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> application).  
	For <def target="def_RuleBased">Network-free</def> applications, only compartmental geometry with 1 compartment is allowed.
	</item>
	<item><bold>Spatial</bold> (1D, 2D or 3D), where geometry of compartments is defined, 
	and species are not well mixed but diffuse within compartments. Such application is 
	simulated using either partial differential equations
	(for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> application), or using stochastic agent-based
	 simulation algorithms SmolDyn
	(for <def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> application).  
	Presently <def target="def_RuleBased">Network-free</def> applications do not allow spatial geometry (compartmental only).
	</item> 
	</list>
	The Application directory displays the Applications associated with the BioModel. The main window 
	displays the selected application and provides buttons to create new applications or to 
	delete or copy applications. Properties for a selected object (e.g. species, reaction, simulation) 
	are displayed in the Properties Pane below the main window.
	</appearance>

	<operations>  
	<para><bold>Create</bold> a new application by clicking on "Applications" in the left menu.  Right 
	click brings a menu to create either a deterministic or stochastic application.  Or, use the 
	<bold> Add New</bold> button in the main window.</para>
	<para><bold>View/Edit application </bold> components and properties by double-clicking the 'Applications' tree item (navigation panel) 
	to expose the names of applications contained in the model, select one of the names to activate the 'view and 'properties' panels that display all the application detail editors.</para>
		<imgReference target = "ApplicationOverview.png">
		</imgReference>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>