<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Composite Species" target="CompositeSpecies">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Composite species</bold> define variables in <link target = "Reactions"> reactions and
 	fluxes</link>. Similar to regular <link target = "RegularSpecies">species</link> they define  
 	unique pools of molecules within a single compartment. <bold>Composite species</bold> 
	have an internal composition: they are composed of <link target = "Molecules">molecules</link> with bonds connecting
	binding sites. If Molecule has multiple states, each state must be specified - otherwise the Species will present a pool
	of different chemical entities and will not be valid. <bold>Composite species</bold>
    can be used as regular species in any reaction network, but they also can serve as seed species in 
	<def target= "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> models: they are either used as starting set of species to 
	generate a network (using <def target= "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> software), or used as an initial set
	of species for stochastic <def target= "def_NetworkFree">Network-free</def> simulations performed by 
	(using <def target= "def_NFSim">NFSim</def> software).
 	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	The Species Tab has several columns:
	<list> 
		<item>The species <bold>Name</bold>. For imported BNGL this name is autogenerated. 
			The user may change name right in the column.</item> 
			<item>the <def target = "def_structure"> structure </def> 
				that contains a species. For rule-based models, this field is uneditable, 
				as a model may contain only one compartment.</item>
			<item>  If the species is linked to a pathway object, a <bold>Link</bold> to that object will be shown in the 
				Link column.  Mousing over a link will open a tooltip box with additional 
				information about the linked object. 
				Double click on that link to navigate to the Pathway Diagram and 
				highlight the object linked to the species.</item>
			<item><bold>Depiction</bold> shows the structure of the species. 
				It shows connected shapes for every molecule that 
				comprise a species, with sites having states marked by yellow dot. States of sites as well as exact
				molecular connectivity is omitted for clarity.</item>
			<item><bold>BioNetGen Definition</bold> provides BNGL string with species encoding. It
				is uneditable but searchable.</item>
	</list> 
	<imgReference target = "CompositeSpecies.GIF"> </imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>Composite species are edited in the <link target = "PP_CompositeSpecies"> Species Properties pane </link> below.</para>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> A species name by highlighting and typing in either table or within the properties pane
	 in the lower window.</para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of species using the Search Box to enter a species name or a structure name.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> species by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.</para>
	<para>If you wish to use <link target = "PathwayOverview"> Pathways Commons</link> data, select the species and use the 
	<link target = "PathLink"> Pathway Links</link> button.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the species within the <link target = "PP_CompositeSpecies"> 
		Species Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
