<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Molecules" target="Molecules">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Molecules</bold> are the principal component of rule-based model specification. 
	They are used to create <link target = "Species">Species</link>, 
	define <link target = "ReactionRules"> Reaction Rules</link> and 
	<link target="Observables">Observables</link>. 
	Molecules are structured objects comprised of components (called <bold>sites</bold>) that can
	bind to each other, both within a molecule and between molecules. <bold>Sites</bold> typically
	represent physical parts of proteins, such as the SH2 and SH3 domains of the adapter protein
	Grb2. <bold>Sites</bold> may also be associated with a list of states, 
	intended to represent states or properties of the site, e.g. phosphorylation status  	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	The Molecules Tab displays a table of the Molecule <bold>name</bold>, <bold>Depiction</bold> of each molecule and the 
	<def target = "def_BioNetGen"> BioNetGen </def> definition that is unediatble but searchable. 
	In the Cartoon, green circle denotes 
	molecular site, while small yellow circle denotes that this Site has possible states. 
	Selecting molecule brings the <link target = "PP_Molecules">Molecule Properties</link> 
	in the bottom right pane, where a user can specify and edit a selected <bold>Molecule</bold>.
	<imgReference target = "BNG_MoleculesTable.png"> </imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>New Molecule</bold> Once a molecule is entered here, a new <link target="Observables">observable</link>
	with a name Molecule_tot is defined. It counts amounts of all instances of this molecule in all species.
	If the Molecule is conserved (not synthesized or degraded), then the observable Molecule_tot will be conserved - 
	it is one possible verifi cation of model consistency.</para>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> A molecule name can be specified and edited in a table, but molecular properties 
	must be specified in 
	the <link target = "PP_Molecules">Molecule Properties</link> bottom pane. 
	Molecule edited here is updated 
	everywhere in the model - in <link target = "Species">Species</link>, 
	 <link target = "ReactionRules"> Reaction Rules</link> and <link target="Observables">Observables</link>.  
    </para>
	<para> <bold>Search</bold> the list of molecules by entering a name 
	or an element of molecular structure below the table.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> molecules by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.
	Molecule will not be deleted if it is used elsewhere in the model.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the molecules within the <link target = "PP_Molecules"> 
	Molecule Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
