<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Molecules Table" target="Molecules">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Molecules</bold> are the principal component of rule-based model specification. 
	They are used to create <link target = "SpeciesTabView">Species</link> and to define <link target = "ReactTabView"> Reaction Rules</link> and <link target="Observables">Observables</link>. 
	Molecules are structured objects comprised of <bold>sites</bold> that can
	bind other sites, either within a single molecule or between molecules. <bold>Sites</bold> typically
	represent physical parts (e.g. domains) of proteins. <bold>Sites</bold> may also be associated with a list of states, 
	intended to represent states or properties of the site, e.g. phosphorylation status.  	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	The Molecules Table displays the Molecule <bold>name</bold>, a <bold>Depiction</bold> of each molecule and the 
	<def target = "def_BioNetGen"> BioNetGen </def> definition of the molecule. 
	In the molecular <bold>depiction</bold>, green circles denote molecular Sites, and an associated small yellow circle denotes a Site that has possible states. 
	Selecting a molecule brings the <link target = "PP_Molecules">Molecule Properties</link> 
	pane to the bottom right of the workspace, where a user can specify and edit a selected <bold>Molecule</bold>.
	<imgReference target = "BNG_MoleculesTable.png"> </imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>New Molecule</bold> creates a new molecule with a default name of <bold>MT'number'</bold>, and also creates a new <link target="Observables">observable</link> with the defaul name of <bold>O'number'_MT'number'_tot.</bold> The Observable tracks the amounts of all instances of the molecule in all species. (Note that if the Molecule is conserved (i.e. not synthesized or degraded), then the observable <bold>Molecule_tot</bold> will be conserved, which is one possible verification of model consistency.)</para>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> the molecule name in the table; molecular properties cannot be edited in the table, but must be specified in the <link target = "PP_Molecules">Molecule Properties</link> pane.</para> 
	<para> <bold>Search</bold> the list of molecules by entering a name 
	or an element of molecular structure in the Search box below the table.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> molecules by selecting the row and using the Delete button below the table. A molecule will not be deleted if it is used elsewhere in the model.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about a molecules within the <link target = "PP_Molecules"> 
	Molecule Properties pane </link>.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
