<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Observables" target="Observables">

	<introduction>
	The <bold>observables</bold> are used to specify model outputs, which are functions of the
	population levels of multiple chemical species that share a set of properties. For example, to
	simulate the tyrosine phosphorylation level of a particular protein, one need to specify
	<bold>Observable</bold> that is a function for the total amount of all chemical species containing 
	the phosphorylated form of this protein. 
	<bold>Observables</bold> are computed over a set of chemical species that share similar properties. 
	<bold>Observables</bold>  may count: 
	<list>
	<item> <bold>Molecules</bold> - a <bold>weighted</bold> sum of the population levels of the chemical 
	species matching the pattern(s)
	in the observable. Each population level is multiplied by the number of times that the species is
	matched by the pattern(s). For example, a species that has two instances of a receptor is counted twice.
	</item>
	<item><bold>Species</bold> - an unweighted sum of
	the population levels of the matching chemical species. 
	For example, a species that has two instances of a receptor is counted once.
	</item> 
	</list>	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		The Observables Tab displays 
		<list>
			<item><bold>Name</bold> of Observable.</item>
			<item><bold>Structure</bold> where species selected by Observable are located 
			(currently, a single compartment only).</item>
			<item><bold>Depiction</bold> of each Observable. Green circle within each molecular shape denote 
			molecular sites, small yellow circles denote that this site has possible states. </item> 
			<item><def target = "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> definition that is unediatble but searchable.</item> 
		</list>
	<imgReference target = "BNG_ObservablesTable.png"> </imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> An Observable name can be specified and edited in a table, but definition and properties 
	must be specified in 
	the <link target = "PP_Observables">Observables Properties</link> bottom pane. 
    </para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of observables using the Search Box to enter a name or any part of observable composition.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> observable by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the observable within the <link target = "PP_Observables"> 
	Observable Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
