<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Observables Table" target="Observables">

	<introduction>
	The <bold>observables</bold> are used to specify model outputs, which are functions of the
	population levels of multiple chemical species that share a set of properties. For example, to
	simulate the tyrosine phosphorylation level of a particular protein, one need to specify
	<bold>Observable</bold> that is a function for the total amount of all chemical species containing 
	the phosphorylated form of this protein.  
	<list>
	<item>Each Observable consists of one or more <bold>Species Patters</bold>. Observable selects species that match at least one
	of the species patterns (not both). </item>
	<item>Each species pattern defines common features of species. It consists of one 
	or more of <link target = "Molecules">molecules</link> that compose
	species. Molecules may or may not be explicitely connected, but must be present 
	in every species selected by this species pattern. Sites that have possible multiple states have yellow sign above site shape. </item>
	<item>Each molecule within species pattern may have some sites being undefined. If site  
	does not have defined states (if states are possible) and its binding is not important, it is shown in white.</item>
	<item>Sites may have defined binding - they can be declared to be explicitly bound to another site, 
	declared unbound or declared bound to "some" (unspecified) site - then the site is shown in green with bond (if exists) 
	shown in solid color.</item>
	<item>Site than has defined state is always shown in green.</item>
	</list>
		<imgReference target = "observables.PNG"> </imgReference>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>

		The Observables Tab displays 
		<list>
			<item><bold>Name</bold> of Observable (editable).</item>
			<item><bold>Structure</bold> where species selected by Observable are located 
			(currently, a single compartment only).</item>
			<item><bold>Depiction</bold> of each Observable. Green circle within each molecular shape denote 
			molecular sites, small yellow circles denote that this site has possible states. </item> 
			<item><def target = "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> definition that is unediatable but searchable.</item> 
			<item> <bold>Count</bold> either <bold>Molecules</bold> or <bold>Species</bold>. In the first case, the output is
			a <bold>weighted</bold> sum of the population levels of the chemical 
			species matching the pattern(s) in the observable. Each population level is multiplied by the number of times that the species is
			matched by the pattern(s). For example, a species that has two instances of a receptor is counted twice.
			In the second case, the output is an <bold>unweighted</bold> sum of
			the population levels of the matching chemical species. 
			For example, a species that has two instances of a receptor is counted once.</item> 
		</list>	
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> An Observable name can be specified and edited in a table, but definition and properties 
	must be specified in 
	the <link target = "PP_Observables">Observables Properties</link> bottom pane. 
    </para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of observables using the Search Box to enter a name or any part of observable composition.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> observable by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the observable within the <link target = "PP_Observables"> 
	Observable Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
