<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reaction Rules" target="ReactionRules">

	<introduction>
		<bold> Reaction Rules </bold> describe describe transformations of species classes by 
		specifying the initial state and consequence of transformation.
		Each reaction rule has three basic elements: reactant pattern(s), product pattern(s), and a rate law specification. 
		<para> 
		Reactant patterns select sets of reactant species undergoing transformation. Product patterns define the end result
		of transformation. Reaction rule is specified in <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesEditor">Editor</link> bottom pane by separate
		declaring of reactants and product patterns, that consist of previously defined molecules. Product pattern may differ 
		from reactant by re-assigning molecules, adding or deleting bonds and changing site states. The VCell editor will enable
		only correct specification of each reactant and product pattern, but will not check if the reaction rule is possible, e.g. 
		if molecules in reactants and products match. 
		</para>
		<para> The default rate law is Mass Action specified in <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesKinetics">Kinetics</link> bottom pane. 
		Every reaction generated by the rule is assigned a rate given by the product of a 
		multiplicity factor generated automatically by BioNetGen , the specified rate constants (which may be a numerical value or a formula), 
		and the population levels of the reactants. 
		</para>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "ReactRulesTable.png"/> 
	<para>
	The table shows the reactions and reaction rules, a user defined name for the reaction (if no name is defined, an automatic name is generated), 
	the structure where the reaction rule occurs (currently <bold>c0 only</bold>), reaction depiction
	and the type of kinetic law governing the reaction (currently <bold>MassAction only</bold>).
	If the reaction rule is linked to a pathway object, a link to that object will be shown in the Link column (currently disabled). 
	</para>
	 <para>The bottom pane of the window displays a <link target = "PP_ReactionRules"> Reaction Rules Proper</link> pane.</para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>Operations with Reaction Rules</bold>
	<list>
		<item> <bold> Create </bold> new Reaction Rule using  <bold>Add New Rule</bold> button, and then pasting or typing a new rule in BNGL code.
		Once entered, the BNGL code is becoming uneditable, and the only way to edit is via <link target = "PP_ReactionRules">properties pane</link>.
		</item>
		 <item> <bold> View and edit</bold> existing reaction rules using  
		<link target = "PP_ReactionRules">properties pane</link>  in the bottom of the window.  
		</item>
		</list>
	</operations>
</page>
</vcelldoc>