<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reaction Rules" target="ReactionRules">

	<introduction>
		<bold> Reaction Rules </bold> are defined alongside regular reactions and 
		describe transformations of species.  
		Each reaction rule has three basic elements: reactant pattern(s), product pattern(s), and a rate law specification. 
		
		<list>
		<item><bold>Reactant pattern(s)</bold> select reactant species undergoing transformation. </item>
		<item><bold>Product pattern(s)</bold> define the end result of transformation. Product pattern may differ 
		from reactant by re-assigning molecules, adding or deleting bonds and changing site states.</item> 
		<item>The default <bold>rate law</bold> is Mass Action specified in <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesKinetics">Kinetics</link> bottom pane. 
		Every reaction generated by the rule is assigned a rate given by the product of a 
		multiplicity factor generated automatically by BioNetGen , 
		the specified rate constants (which may be a numerical value or a formula), 
		and the population levels of the reactants.</item>
		</list> 
		Reaction rule is specified in <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesEditor">Editor</link> bottom pane by 
		declaring reactant patterns, that consist of previously defined molecules.  The VCell editor will enable
		only correct specification of each reactant and product pattern. 
	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	The Reactions Tab has several columns:
	<list> 
		<item><bold>Reaction</bold> column has uneditable Reaction Rule mark in place of reaction notation for 
		regular <link target = "ReactTabView">reactions</link>. </item> 
		<item><bold>Name</bold> column has a sortable name that is autogenerated as r_number but can be edited.</item> 
		<item><def target = "def_structure">structure </def> 
			that contains a rule. For rule-based models, this field is uneditable, 
			as a model may contain only one compartment.</item>
		<item><bold>Depiction</bold> shows the structure of the reactant and product species patterns. Green sites 
			have either binding or state specified, white sites are undefined and can be connected to anything or be
			in multiple states (if yellow shape is shown).States of sites is omitted for clarity.</item>
		<item><bold>Kinetics</bold> is Mass Action and is currently uneditable.</item>
		<item><bold>BioNetGen Definition</bold> provides BNGL string with rule encoding. It
			is uneditable but searchable.</item>
		<item><bold>Link</bold> does not work for reaction rules at this time.</item>
	</list> 
	<imgReference target = "ReactRulesTable.png"></imgReference>
	
	 <para>The bottom pane of the window displays a 
	 	<link target = "PP_ReactionRules"> Reaction Rules Properties</link> pane.</para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>Operations with Reaction Rules</bold>
	<list>
		<item> <bold>New Rule</bold> will create a new Reaction Rule. The only way to edit 
		the new rule is via <link target = "PP_ReactionRules">properties pane</link> below.</item>
		<item> <bold>Search</bold> the list of reactions and reaction rules using the Search Box 
		to enter reaction rule name or any part of BNGL string.</item>
		<item><bold>Delete</bold> reaction and reaction rules by highlighting and using 
		the "Delete" button below the table.</item>
		<item><bold>Duplicate</bold> will create an exact copy of highlighted rule 
		with a new name oldname_0. This is very useful
		feature when a new rule is a slight modification of the previous one.</item>
		<item><bold>View, edit or Add annotation</bold> for existing reaction rules using  
		<link target = "PP_ReactionRules">Editor</link> pane in the bottom of the window.</item>
		<item><bold>Edit kinetics</bold> for existing reaction rules using  
		<link target = "PP_ReactionRulesKinetics">Kinetics</link> pane in the bottom of the window.</item>		
		</list>
	</operations>
</page>
</vcelldoc>