<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Species Table" target="SpeciesTabView">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Species</bold> are used to create variables (molecular species) in <def target = "def_reactions">reactions</def> and fluxes and can exist in both <def target = "def_membranes">  membranes </def> and 
 	<def target = "def_compartments"> volume compartments </def> (volumes). 
 	Species are unique pools of molecules within a single structure; if the same species is copied to a different 
 	structure, the structure name is appended to the species name to retain a unique identifier, e.g. species_structure. A species is depicted in the <link target = "ReactDiagView">Reaction Diagram</link> as a green shape.
 	
 	<para>For use in <def target = "def_RuleBased">rule-based modeling</def> species must
	have molecular details specified: they are composed of <link target = "Molecules">molecules</link> with bonds connecting
	binding sites. If Molecule has multiple states, each state must be specified - otherwise the species will present a pool
	of different chemical entities and will not be valid. Species with molecular details
    can be used as regular species in any reaction network, but they also can serve as seed species in 
	<def target= "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> models: they are either used as starting set of species to 
	generate a network (using <def target= "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> software), or used as an initial set
	of species for stochastic <def target= "def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> simulations performed by 
	(using <def target= "def_NFSim">NFSim</def> software).</para>
 	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "Mix_Species.PNG"> </imgReference>
	<para>The Species Tab has several columns:</para>
	<list> 
		<item>The species <bold>Name</bold>.  For new species it will be s_number. For imported BNGL this name is autogenerated. 
			The user may change name right in the column.</item> 
			<item>the <def target = "def_structure"> structure </def> 
				that contains a species.</item>
			<item>  If the species is linked to a pathway object, a <bold>Link</bold> to that object will be shown in the 
				Link column.  Mousing over a link will open a tooltip box with additional 
				information about the linked object. 
				Double click on that link to navigate to the Pathway Diagram and 
				highlight the object linked to the species.</item>
			<item><bold>Depiction</bold> shows the structure of the species. For species without molecular details it will be green shape.
				For species with moledcular details it will shows connected shapes for every molecule that 
				comprise a species, with sites having states marked by yellow dot. States of sites are omitted for clarity.</item>
			<item><bold>BioNetGen Definition</bold> provides BNGL string for species with molecular detail. Ends of the same bonds are show with the same color. This field is uneditable but searchable.</item></list> 
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> molecular details of species in the 
	<link target = "PP_Species">Species Properties pane</link> in the lower window.</para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of species using the Search Box to enter a species name or a structure name.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> species by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.</para>
	<para>If you wish to use <link target = "PathwayOverview"> Pathways Commons</link> data, select the species and use the 
	<link target = "PathLink"> Pathway Links</link> button.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the species within the <link target = "PP_Species"> 
		Species Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
