<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Network-Free Specifications"  target="NetworkFreeSpecifications">
	
	<introduction>
		A Network-Free simulation (using the NFSim solver) can be run for BioModels that include only a single compartment and where all reactions in the model have mass action kinetics.  For Biomodels without rules or molecular definitions, the simulations results will generate equivalent results as when using a non-spatial stochastic solver. The Network-free Specifications tab is visible only in Network-Free Applications. When a NetworkFree simulation is run for a non-ruled based BioModel, the Physiology is first coverted into a rule-based model and the simulation is run using the NFSim solver.  Within this Specifications window, it is possible to save the rule-based model that will be created as a new VCell Biomodel.

	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		Statistics of the species, molecules, reactions and observables are provided for both the original physiology and the created rule based physiology.  If the original model is rule-based, these numbers will be identical.  
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<imgReference target = "NetworkFreeTab.PNG"/>
	<para>	
<bold>Create New Rule-Based VCell BioModel</bold> from the original physiology. A new BioModel is created and opened in a new window. A rule based model can be created only for models with a single compartment and if all reactions have mass action kinetics.  Molecules, observables, species with molecular details, and reaction rules are transferred to a new
BioModel without changes. Species without molecular details and reactions are converted into rule-based physiology by generating a molecule for each species, and converting reactions to fully-defined reaction rules.</para>

	<para>
	Note that the same reaction expression treated as a reaction and as a reaction rule will have different rates:
	</para>
	
	<list><item>VCell will automatically convert reactions of the form A + A -> product(s), by multiplying the rate of  the generated reaction rules by 2 to account for symmetry factors. </item>
		<item>VCell does not take adjust the kinetics of reactions where reactants have symmetric sites and where the reaction rule has a statistical factor. If this is not properly corrected by the user, the resultant rule-based model may yield different simulation results than its network precursor. </item>
	</list>
	
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>