<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Network Specifications"  target="NetworkSpecifications">

	
	<introduction>
	For <def target = "def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> and <def target = "def_Stochastic">stoichastic</def> applications, 
	Network Tab describes constraints for network-generation performed by <def target = "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> engine, and tests
	the size of the reaction network that is obtained using these constraints. 
	Only after the user applies changes, the <link target="simulations_overview">simulation</link> 
	is performed on the generated reaction network.
	This tab is active only if at least one <link target="Molecules">Molecule</link> is specified.  	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "NetworkTab.PNG"/>
	<list>
		<item><bold>Max Iterations</bold> - how many times the rules are applied to the set of 
		<def target = "def_SeedSpecies">seed species</def> to generate new species and reactions.</item>
		<item><bold>Max Molecules/Species</bold> - the maximal number of molecules of any type that can be in a single species. 
		BioNetGen  will not apply any rules to species reaching this limit.</item>
		<item><bold>Species</bold> - the total number of species in the reaction network generated under
		specified constraints, including seed species.</item>
		<item><bold>Reactions</bold> - the total number of reactions in the reaction network generated under
		specified constraints.</item>
	</list>	
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
After clicking on "Edit/Test Constraints" button, a user is presented with a window to specify new constraints. 	
<imgReference target = "NetworkConstraints.PNG"/>	
<list>	
	<item><bold>Test/Run</bold> will attempt to generate a reaction network using these constraints.</item>
	<item><bold>Apply</bold> will apply these constraints without network generation, 
	so the <link target="simulations_overview">simulation</link> will be performed sequentially after network generation.</item>
</list>

Running network may generate some warnings:
<list>
	<item>
		<bold>Max iterations number may be insufficient</bold> means that the network may be not exaustively generated. In the
		<bold>Network Generation Status</bold> pane below one can see that the number of species during the last two iterations is
		different. Normally, the network generation stops when the last iteration does not produce new species, which means that
		the number of species at the last two iterations are the same.
		<imgReference target = "MaxIterNumber.PNG"/> 
	</item>
	<item>
		<bold>Max Molecules/Species number may be not sufficient</bold> means that the species with the set number of molecules are still
		subject to rules application, so the network is truncated by this limitation.
		<imgReference target = "MaxMolec.PNG"/>
	</item>
</list>	
<bold>Note:</bold> When the warning is displayed, the network is trunkated, which means that NFSim simulation will
		likely produce different results than deterministic or stochastic simulations that use this network.
	</operations>
	
	<para>When <bold>Apply</bold> button is pressed, the constrains are applied to the application, and the user can
	<bold>View</bold> all generated species and reactions, as well as <bold>Create a new VCell BioModel</bold> that consist 
	of all generated species and reactions. This new model is not rule-based, but all species have molecular detail spe specified.</para>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>