<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reactions Specifications"  target="ReactionsSpecifications">

	
	<introduction>
	There is often a wide range of time scales in interrelated cellular processes that pose a problem when computing numerical solutions. 
	The Virtual Cell software has been designed based on the separation of fast and slow kinetics. 
	The user can specify the subset of reactions that have fast kinetics and the fast system will automatically be generated and integrated into the mathematical description by selecting or deselecting the option.
	This is done in the <bold>Reactions Specifications</bold> panel.	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		<bold>Deterministic</bold>
		<imgReference target = "ReactionsSpecifications_determ.png"/>  
		<para><bold>Stochastic</bold>
		<imgReference target = "ReactionsSpecifications_stoch.png"/> 
		</para>
	</appearance>
		
	<operations>
	<bold>Viewing/Editing Reactions Specifications</bold>
	Select a reaction from the table to display the <link target="PP_Reactions">Reactions Properties Pane</link> in the <link target="GeneralNavAndWinSetup">Properties panel</link> below.
	View reaction properties in the <link target="PP_Reactions">Reactions Properties Pane</link>.
	To edit reaction properties, See <link target="ReactTabView">Reactions table</link>.
	Common information includes reaction 'Name', 'Type' (regular, flux, rule) and 'Enabled' (set/unset whether a reaction is included in simulations).
	<list>
	<item><bold>Turn off reactions</bold> in simulations by un-checking the checkbox under the <bold>Enabled</bold> table column causing solvers to ignore the reaction during simulations.  
	A mouse popup menu can also be used to enable/disable a reaction.</item>
	<item><bold>Set Fast mode</bold> for reactions in <bolod>deterministic applications</bolod> by checking the box under the <bold>Fast</bold> table column causing reaction to be treated as pseudo-steady-state.  
	May increases the speed of simulation processing and reduce the time needed to run a simulation.</item>
	<item><bold>By default </bold> all reactions are <bold>enabled</bold> and <bold>not fast</bold>. </item>
	</list>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>