<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	<link target = "target"> put your link here </link>
	<imgReference target = "target"/>
	<def target = "target"> put your link here </def>
    
    NOTE: introduction is required. 
          Please save your file as ".xml" in to VCell/UserDocumentation/your chapter name.
          Please be noted no space and special chars are allowed in the file name. 
          Please name your target as the file name(you are linking to) without extension. (e.g to set a link to Phys_Struct.html, you write target = "Phys_Struct"). 
          Before you commit, please try it out in browser first.
-->
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Simulations">

	
	<introduction>
	You can run a simulation once you have defined your physiology and created an Application in a BioModel or have defined your math using VCell Math Description Language in a MathModel.
	</introduction>
	
	<introduction>
	The Virtual Cell automatically converts the biological description defined in a BioModel into a corresponding mathematical system of ordinary and/or partial differential equations.
	The Virtual Cell will then solve the equations by applying numerical solvers to perform and analyze simulations. Afterwards Results can be displayed and analyzed on-line 
	or downloaded to the user’s computer in a variety of formats.
	
	There are 4 categories of simulations.
	<list>
	<item>deterministic non-spatial</item>
	The compartmental simulation executes a single point simulation based on the defined physiological model, the geometric assumptions, and structure sizes or surface to volume ratios and
	volume fractions. The ordinary differential equations (ODE), for single point approximations, representing the reactions kinetics are generated and passed to an interpreted ODE solver.
	The set of nonlinear ODE equations are typically solved in seconds. It allows an interactive modification 
	of parameters and a quick determination of the effect over time. In addition, the Virtual Cell software computes the local sensitivity (Sensitivity Analysis) of any species concentration 
	to any parameter as a function of time evaluated at the nominal solution.	
	<item>stochastic non-spatial</item>
	<item>deterministic spatial</item>
	<item>stochastic spatial</item>
	</list>
 	</introduction>
	
	<appearance><imgReference target = "simulations.jpg"/></appearance>
	
	<operations>  </operations>
	
	<comments> 
	The appropriate solver for deterministic/stochastic compartmental models or spatial models will automatically be chosen.
	</comments>

</page>

</vcelldoc>