<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Simulations Editor">

	
	<introduction>
	In the "Simulation" tab, highlight the simulation you want to edit and clicking the "Edit Simulation" button leads to you a simulation editor.
	The simulation editor has two tabs, which are "Parameters" and "Solvers".
	</introduction>
	<appearance><imgReference target="sim_simEditor.gif"/></appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Parameters</bold></para>
	<para>Displays a summary list of the Parameters, the Default, Changed or Scanned Values used in the simulation. VCell
is able to run complex simulations in which one or more parameters vary according to a specified list or range of
possible values. Altering parameter values allows you to quickly and easily modify your model description without
having to make a complete new BioModel or access the BioModel dialog. Parameter scans enable the user to do
“brute force” exploration of the parameter space of a model in a single simulation specification without
having to manually create, edit, and run many individual simulations that would test the different combinations
of parameter values.</para>
	<list>
	<item>Change Value</item>
	<para>The Simulation Editor window allows the user to override the default value of any parameter by specifying a
	 different value to be used during the simulation. The value can be a numerical value or mathematical expressions. Identify the Parameter Name and Double click on the New
	Value/Expression field to type in a new value or expression. Press Enter to accept the value. Note that values that have changed appear in red.
	</para>
    <item>Scan</item>
    <para>To specify a parameter scan, one must check the corresponding checkbox for the parameter
	(s), and a dialog box will appear where the user can enter a List or Range of values to be scanned.
	</para>
	<para><imgReference target="sim_scan.gif"/></para>
	<para>List- Enter values separated by commas. Each value will be used in a simulation.</para>
	<para>Range - Enter the values that will be used as the minimum and maximum values between
which intermediates are calculated as equal interval values.</para>
	<para>Range Log - When the checkbox ‘log’ is used, the intermediate values between the minimum
and maximum are calculated as equal ratio values - e.g. for the example shown, the four values would be 0.1, 1.0, 10, and 100. This
allows scanning over several orders of magnitude in a progressive way.
	</para>
	<para>When more than one parameter is checked for scanning, the simulation will
be performed with all possible combinations of values for all scanned parameters. The figure shows the Simulation Editor window for
such a simulation, where 2 parameters were specified for scans, one with a list of 3 values, and one over a range of 2 values,
resulting in a total of 6 different combinations for which the simulation is run.
	</para>
	</list>
	</operations>
	
	<comments> 
	</comments>

</page>

</vcelldoc>