<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="How to simulate a rule-based model" target="RBCreate">

	<introduction> 
	Once rule-based features are specified in the BioModel Physiology, several numerical methods can be used to run simulations. As is the case with all Virtual Cell BioModels, a Rule-Based BioModel may have multiple
	Applications, including <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> and 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> (<def target="def_RuleBased">rule-based</def>) applications; in addition, for rule-based models <def target="def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> applications can be created.  Each Application, in turn, can have multiple Simulations, in which different numerical
	methods or conditions are used.	</introduction>	

	<operations>
	<para><bold>Rule-based Deterministic and Stochastic Applications</bold></para>
	<para>When a <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> or 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> application of a rule-based model is created, the <def target="def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> network-generation algorithm is used to generate the complete network of species and reactions 
	that is obtained by applying the set of reaction rules to the 
	set of <def target="def_SeedSpecies">seed species</def>. Initial amounts
	of seed species are defined in the <link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> specification tab.
	<link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> specification parameters 
	(number of iterations to apply rules and maximum number of molecules per species in the generated network) 
	are used to control the size of the network,
	which otherwise can become infinitely large. The generated species and reactions can be viewed in the
	<link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> or the 
	<link target = "ReactDiagView">Reaction Diagram</link> view. </para>
	
	<para>After the network is generated, determiministic or 
		stochastic <link target = "simulations_overview">simulations</link> can be run as for any Application.</para>
	
	<para><bold>Network-Free Applications</bold></para>
	<para>In <def target="def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> applications of a rule-based BioModel, 
	a network is not generated. Instead, the amounts of model <link target = "Observables">Observables</link> 
	and initially defined <link target = "SpeciesTabView">species</link> are simulated using 
	the <def target="def_NFSim">NFSim</def> engine. Simulation parameters are defined in the
	<link target = "NFSimSimulationEditor">NFSim Simulation Editor</link>.</para>
	
	
	<para><bold>Rule-Based MathModel</bold></para>

	<para>The MathModel for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> or 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> applications generated for rule-based models 
	have a standard VCell structure that includes the full list of species and reactions, and includes observables
	defined by functions. The MathModel for <def target="def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> applications has a unique syntax.	</para>

	</operations>
	
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>