<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Overview of Rule-Based Features" target="RuleBasedOverview">

	<introduction> 
The Virtual Cell Software now provides an integrated environment to 
introduce <def target= "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> features among species and reactions in a VCell Biomodel. 
Additions to the Biomodel <link target = "PhysOverview">Physiology</link>  include 
<link target = "Molecules">Molecules</link> and <link target = "Observables">Observables</link>, 
as well as <def target = "def_ReactionRules">reaction rules</def> that can be specified alongside 
<def target = "def_reactions">reactions</def> in the <link target = "ReactTabView">Reactions</link> Table.  Defining <link target = "Molecules">Molecules</link> allows the user to create species that have <link target = "PP_Species">molecular details</link>.
 
<para><bold>Mixing Rule-based features and reaction networks</bold></para>
Similar to the traditional BioModel, a rule-based BioModel consists of a model description (Physiology) 
and one or more Applications. Any operations on species and reactions that are supported in VCell can be used alongside rules. Specifically, species that are used as initial <def target= "def_SeedSpecies">seed species</def> for rule-based models can be used as species in reaction networks.


	<para><bold>Rule-based Applications</bold></para>
	Each <link target = "ApplicationOverview">BioModel Application</link> 
	allows the user to define the  quantitative conditions needed to define, 
	run and visualize a numerical simulation.  A Rule-Based BioModel may have mutliple
	Applications, solved using <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def>, 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> or <def target="def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> approaches.  
	Each Application, in turn, can have multiple Simulations, in which different numerical
	methods or conditions are used. 
	<list>
		<item>In order to run <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> or 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> (<def target="def_RuleBased">rule-based</def>) applications
	the <def target="def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> network-generation
	algorithm first generates the complete network of species and reactions.</item> 
	<item>The network is created by applying the set of reaction rules to the set of 
	<def target = "def_SeedSpecies">seed species</def> with initial amounts
	specified in the <link target = "SpeciesSpecifications">Species</link> specification tab.
	<link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> specification parameters are used to control the size of the network,
	which otherwise can become infinitely large. The generated species and reactions can be seen in the 
	<link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> tab. </item>
	<item>After the user is satified with the network that is generated using the set of species and reaction rules, any determiministic or stochastic <link target = "simulations_overview">simulation</link> can be run.
		</item>
	</list>

	<para><bold>Rule-Based MathModel</bold></para>
	MathModels for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> or 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> applications generated by a rule-based model 
	have a standard VCell structure with a full list of species and reactions, as well as observables
	defined by functions. MathModels for <def target="def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> application have a new syntax.

	</introduction>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>