<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Applications Overview" target="ApplicationOverview">

	<introduction>
	Applications allow users to specify the quantitative conditions needed to define, 
	run and visualize a Virtual Experiment, i.e. a numerical simulation of the BioModel 
	with specific initial conditions, within a given geometry, and with a selected type 
	of simulation method. In the Application,
	<list> 
	<item>the mapping between the model and the geometry 
	is established in the <link target="GeometryOverview">Geometry</link> tab</item>
	<item><link target="SpecificationsOverview"> Specifications</link> for species, reactions and network 
	(for rule-based application) are defined,</item> 
	<item>specific <link target="ProtocolsOverview"> Protocols</link> 
	(events, electric stimulation) can be included,</item> 
	<item>for each application, multiple <link target="simulations_overview">Simulations</link> 
	can be created that can include different initial conditions.
	</item>
	<item><link target="PEOverview">Parameter Estimation</link> can be performed.</item> 
	</list>  
	</introduction>

	<appearance>  
	 Applications can be 
	 <list> 
	<item><def target="def_Deterministic">Deterministic</def></item>
	<item><def target="def_Stochastic">Stochastic</def></item>
	<item><def target="def_HybridDeterministicStochastic">Hybrid Deterministic Stochastic</def>, 
	a stochastic model with at least 1 species specification set to 'Force Continuous' 
	(See <bold>Spatial Stochastic </bold> or <bold>Non-Spatial Stochastic </bold>under <link target="SpeciesSpecifications">Species Specifications</link>).</item>
	<item><def target="def_RuleBased">Network-free</def>, a special stochastic <link target="NFSimApp">network-free application</link> that does not require generating a network to simulate. </item> 
	</list>
	<imgReference target = "ApplicationTypes.png"/>
	<para> Additionally, by defining <link target="GeometryOverview">Geometry</link>, deterministic, stochastic or network-free 
	applications can be made:</para>
	<list> 
	<item><bold>Compartmental</bold> (1D, 2D or 3D), where the topology and size of compartments are defined, but species are assumed 
	to be well mixed within their compartments. A compartmental application is simulated using either differential equations
	(for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> application), or using stochastic simulation algorithms 
	(for <def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> application).  
	</item>
	<item><bold>Spatial</bold> (1D, 2D or 3D), where the geometry of compartments is defined, 
	and species diffuse within compartments. A spatial application is 
	simulated using either partial differential equations
	(for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> applications), or using the stochastic agent-based
	 simulation algorithm SmolDyn (for <def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> applications). 
	Deterministic spatial applications can also utilize our moving boundary solver in cases where movement of volumes or surfaces can be described within the simulation.   
	Presently <def target="def_RuleBased">Network-free</def> applications do not allow spatial geometry (compartmental only).
	</item> 
	</list>
	The Application directory displays the Applications associated with the BioModel. The main window 
	displays the selected application and provides buttons to create new applications or to 
	delete or copy applications. Properties for a selected object (e.g. species, reaction, simulation) 
	are displayed in the Properties Pane below the main window.
	</appearance>
	<operations>  
        <bold>Create</bold> a new application by selecting "Applications" in the left menu.  Right 
	click opens a menu to create a deterministic, stochastic, or network-free application.  Or, use the 
	<bold>New Application</bold> button in the main window.
	<para><bold>View/Edit</bold> application components and properties by double-clicking, or selecting the + icon beside, the 'Applications' tree in the navigation panel to expose the names of applications contained in the BioModel; select one of the Application names to activate the 'view' and 'properties' panels that display all the application detail editors.</para>
		<imgReference target = "ApplicationOverview.png"/>
			</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>