<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<vcelldoc>
<page title="Entities Table View">
	
	<introduction> 	
A table of pathway entities can be used to examine their properties and their link status. 
It is the table format representation of the 
		<link target = "PathwayDiagramView"> Entities Diagram View</link>.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>  
The table view shows the pathway entities, their type and also shows which of these 
entities (if any) are linked to corresponding entities within the physiology.
<para>
		<imgReference target = "PathwayObjectsView.png">
		</imgReference>
</para>
<para>
It can be noticed that the selected reaction and its dependents are already 
linked to their respective physiology equivalents.
</para>
<para>
The bottom pane of the window displays a 
		<link target = "PP_Pathways"> Entity Properties Pane</link>. 
In the sample image presented below you can see the properties of the biochemical 
reaction selected in the Pathway Object View above.
</para>
		<imgReference target = "PP_Pathways.png">
		</imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	
	<operations>  
<para>
More entities can be added from the 
		<link target = "PathwayImportTable"> Imported Pathway View</link>.
</para>
<para>
The user can perform various operations upon these entities, either on individually selected 
entities or multiple selected entities using the 
		<link target = "GroupOperationsPanel"> Entities Management Toolbar</link>.
</para>
<para>
Of particular interest is the process of importing pathway entities into the BioModel. 
Following this process, equivalent entities to those pathway entities being imported will 
be created within the Physiology.
</para>
		<imgReference target = "OperationsToolbar.png">
		</imgReference>
<para>
The table items can be sorted alphabetically by any column by clicking on the column header. 
As an added capability, the items in the table can be filtered in real time by typing a string 
inside the Search field. 
</para>
	<imgReference target = "PathwayTableSearch.png"/>
	</operations>
	
	<comments>  </comments>

</page>

</vcelldoc>