<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
	<link target = "target"> put your link here </link>
	<imgReference target = "target"/>
	<def target = "target"> put your link here </def>
    
    NOTE: introduction is required. 
          Please save your file as ".xml" in to VCell/UserDocumentation/your chapter name.
          Please be noted no space and special chars are allowed in the file name. 
          Please name your target as the file name(you are linking to) without extension. (e.g to set a link to Phys_Struct.html, you write target = "Phys_Struct"). 
          Before you commit, please try it out in browser first.
-->
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Simulations Overview">

	
	<introduction>
	Once a MathModel or an 'application' in a BioModel is created at least 1 simulation must be defined to generate numerical results.  You can create, copy, edit, run (local or remote), stop and delete simulations. 
	The simulations panel also shows the running status (% progress,results available) of all simulations.  
	Select a simulation row to 
	display additional information in the properties panel below, 
	launch a data viewer for simulation that have been run 
	and display parameter scan information.
	Model parameters can be changed for each simulation without changing the overall model.  
	Simulation parameter scans can be defined to iterate over a set of model parameters, automatically generating separate results for each combination of parameter values.  
	The panel also contains 'Output Functions' to add user defined data expressions that are displayed when simulation results are shown.
 	</introduction>
	
	<appearance><imgReference target="sim_overview.png"/></appearance>
	
	<operations>
	There are three sub-tabs under "Simulations" tab:
	<list>
	<item>
	Click <link target="simulations">Simulations</link> tab to create and run a simulation.
	</item>
	<item>
	Click <link target="output_functions">Output Functions</link> tab to define an output function.
	</item>
	<item>
	Click <link target="generated_math">Generated Math</link> tab to view generated math.
	</item>
	</list>
	<para></para>
	<para>
	<bold>Right-clicking</bold> on a simulation row will reveal a drop down submenu providing a way to edit End Time and Output Option (frequency of saved data points).
	<imgReference target="SimulationsMenuRightClick.PNG"/>
	</para>
	 </operations>
	
	<comments> 
	</comments>

</page>

</vcelldoc>