<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="File">

	<introduction>
	The <bold>File</bold> menu allows the user to perform several file operations on the currently open VCell Document.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		<imgReference target = "FileMenu.PNG"/>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations> 
	Clicking the File menu displays a popup menu with the following choices: 
	<list>
 	  <item>
		<link target = "New">New</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>	  
		<link target = "Open">Open</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>		
		<bold> Close </bold> - closes the currently open document,
	  </item>
	  <item>
		<bold> Save </bold> - saves the current document to database, overwriting the older version. Note that this menu option is disabled for a new document. 
		For saving a new document, refer to <link target = "SaveAs">Save As</link>. 
		Also, when the user modifies a public model or a model that has been shared by another user and tries to save the model, the "Save" option is enabled. 
		Choosing this option brings up a warning dialog that the model does not belong to the current user and it has to be saved as a new model in the current user's account. 
		Clicking <link target = "SaveAs">Save As</link> brings up the "Save As" dialog. <bold>Cancel</bold> cancels the save operation.    
	</item>
	</list>
		<para>
 	  	</para>
	  	<imgReference target = "FileSaveWarning.PNG"/>
 		<para>
 	  <list>
	  <item>		
		<bold> Save New Version </bold> - saves copy of document to database as a new version (with same name but latest time stamp),
	  </item>
	  <item>		
		<link target = "SaveAs">Save As...</link> - saves copy of document to database with new name,
	  </item>
	  <item>		
		<bold>Save As Local...</bold> - saves copy of current document to users local computer (see <link target = "Export">Export...</link>),
	  </item>
	  <item>		
		<link target = "RevertToSaved">Revert To Saved</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>
		<bold>Compare With Saved</bold> -  compares the currently open document with its latest saved version in the database and displays the result in a separate window. 
		Refer to the section on <link target = "ManageDBCompareWith">Compare With</link> for further information. 
	  </item>
	  <item>
		<link target = "Permissions">Permissions...</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>
		<link target = "FieldData">Field Data...</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>		
		<link target = "Import">Import...</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>
		<link target = "Export">Export...</link>,
	  </item>
	  <item>		
		<bold>Exit</bold> - exits the Virtual Cell, closing all open documents and prompting user to save any unsaved document(s).
	  </item>
	</list>	
	</para>	
	</operations>
	
	<comments> </comments>

</page>

</vcelldoc>