<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Introduction" target="GeneralOverview">

	<introduction>
The Virtual Cell Modeling and Simulation Framework (VCell) 
was developed by the National Resource for Cell Analysis and 
Modeling. This unique software platform has been designed to model cell
biological processes. Biochemical and electrophysiological data describing
individual reactions are associated with experimental microscopic 
image data describing their subcellular locations. Cell physiological events 
can then be simulated within the empirically derived geometries, thus facilitating 
the direct comparison of model predictions with experiment.
<para></para>
VCell consists of a biological and mathematical framework. As described in the <link target="General">Overview</link>, users can create 
biological models from which the software will generate the mathematical code 
needed to run simulations.  Mathematicians may opt to use the math framework, 
based on the Virtual Cell Markup Language, for creating their own mathematical descriptions. 
<para></para>
Models can be reused, updated, and made available to the scientific community. In
addition, models may also be privately shared amongst collaborating groups. The data from
simulations are stored on the Virtual Cell database server and are easily exported in a variety of formats.
Access to the Virtual Cell modeling software is available via the internet using a JAVA based interface.
The Virtual Cell has been developed using the latest supported Java technology.
<para></para>
Virtual Cell also supports 
<link target="RuleBasedOverview">rule-based modeling</link>, which allows the representation 
of species as structured objects consisting of <link target="Molecules">molecules</link> 
and uses  <def target = "def_ReactionRules">reaction rules</def> to define molecular interactions that transform the attributes of species. 
The rule-based approach allows one to systematically incorporate site-specific details of
molecular interactions into a model.
	</introduction>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>