<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
    <page title="Overview" target="General">

        <introduction>
            VCell provides two styles of developing computational models:
			<list>
                <item><bold>BioModels</bold></item>
                <item><bold>MathModels</bold></item>
            </list>
            Each uses a different method to create models to best suit a given user's experience.

            <para><bold>BioModel</bold></para>
            A BioModel is a computational model built by defining the biological components of the model within a graphical interface.

            BioModels consist of:
            <para>
            (1) A <link target="PhysOverview">Physiology</link>; the cellular structures, species and biochemical reactions that are components of the model.
            </para>
            <para>
            (2) <link target="ApplicationOverview">Applications</link>; the application of the model to a specific instance of physiology,in which the initial state and any additional conditions or constraints on the physiology are defined.
            </para>

            Each <link target="ApplicationOverview">Application</link>
            allows the user to define the quantitative values needed to define, run and visualize a Virtual
            Experiment (i.e. numerical simulation). Thus, an <bold>Application</bold> includes:
            <list>
                <item><link target="GeometryOverview">Geometry</link></item>
                <item><link target="SpecificationsOverview">Specifications</link> (e.g. species, reactions)</item>
                <item><link target="ProtocolsOverview">Protocols</link> (e.g. events, electrical mapping)</item>
                <item><link target="simulations_overview">Simulations</link>, of which there can be one or more.</item>
                <item><link target="PEOverview">Parameter Estimation</link> (if applicable) for defining parameters based on experimental data</item>
			</list>

            <para><bold>MathModel</bold></para>
            MathModels create individual Applications (Virtual Experiments) using the <bold>Virtual Cell Markup Language</bold> (<bold>VCML</bold>).  VCell automatically creates a unique MathModel for each Application within a BioModel; such MathModels can be created ad hoc or edited using VCML.  Note that a MathModel does not have an associated Physiology.
            A MathModel consists of a series of definitions for:
            <list>
                <item>Constants</item>
                <item>Variables</item>
                <item>Functions</item>
                <item>Volume domains</item>
                <item>Membrane domains</item>
            </list>
            See <link target="generated_math">Generated Math</link> for more information on the components of the math description and how to <bold>create</bold> a stand-alone MathModel from an existing BioModel Application that can then be further edited.


        </introduction>

    </page>

</vcelldoc>