<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="General Navigation and Window Setup">

	
	<introduction>
	The Virtual Cell GUI now incorporates elements required for rule-based modeling, 
	with improved mechanisms to add <def target = "def_species">species</def>, <def target = "def_reactions"> reactions</def>, and model <def target = "def_structure" >structures</def>.
	The document view displays the model at a glance, with intuitive tabs and tree structures that allows the user to navigate a Biomodel with ease.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		<imgReference target = "VCellMain.png"/> 
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>
	The VCell document window has a <link target="TopMenu">top-level menu</link> that allows the user to perform various operations on the VCell document, such as save or export a model, share a model for collaborative viewing, etc. 
	The document window has 4 panels that present the user with a canvas to browse, create and maintain a model. 
	</para>
	<list>
		<item>
		<para><bold>Navigation panel (Panel A)</bold></para>
		<para>
		The top left panel is the Navigation panel that allows the user to navigate the currently open model. 
		The tree structure displays the Physiology (<link target="ReactDiagView">Reaction Diagram</link>, 
		<link target="ReactTabView">Reactions</link> (tabular view), 
		<link target="PhysStructTabView">Structures</link> (compartments), <link target="SpeciesTabView">Species</link>,
		<link target="Molecules">Molecules</link> and <link target="Observables">Observables</link>), the list of <link target="ApplicationOverview">Applications</link>, 
		<link target="ParametersAndFunctionsOverview">Parameters and Functions</link>, and <link target="PathwayOverview">Pathway</link> related information.
		Clicking on any item in the tree will display the item in the <bold>View</bold> panel (panel B, top right panel). 
		For example, choosing the "Reaction" item under "Physiology" will open the table of reactions in the model in the 'View' panel or choosing "Reaction Diagram" in the navigator tree will display the model reaction network in the 'View' panel.
		</para>
		<para>
		Clicking on the top level entity of the navigation tree in the "Navigation" panel (typically represented by the name of the VCell model) displays a summary of the model in the "View" panel. 
		The summary information contains such details as the model's name, owner, last modified date, permissions to view the model (also refer to <link target="Permissions">File -> Permissions</link>), and a brief summary of the applications in the model.
		</para>
		</item>

		<item>
		<para><bold>View panel (Panel B)</bold></para>
		<para>
		The top right panel in the figure above is the 'View' panel. The default view (Physiology view) has the following 6 tabs that allow the user to create a physiological model before he/she can run simulations. 
		<bold>Reaction Diagram</bold> is used to view the reaction network and add species or reactions and fluxes to the model. 
		<bold>Reactions</bold> lists the reactions in the model in a tabular form. The user can also add/delete reactions here. 
		<bold>Structures</bold> lists the compartments in the model as a table. Compartments can also be added or deleted in this table.
		<bold>Species</bold> lists the species of the model in a table.
		<bold>Molecules</bold> list the seed species for a rule-based model and depict the possible states for each molecule.
		<bold>Observables</bold> list the functions that define groups of molecular states or species that are created in rule-based models.
		</para>
		</item>

		<item>
		<para><bold>Properties panel (Panel C)</bold></para>
		<para>
		This is the panel on the bottom right of the VCell document window. This panel contains the following 3 tabs.
		The <bold>Object Properties</bold> tab displays the properties of any entity (species, reaction, structure) selected in any of the tabs in the "View" panel (refer to section <link target="PropertiesPaneOverview">Properties Pane</link>) panel.
		The <bold>Problems</bold> tab lists the errors and warnings in the model that has been created. The user is not allowed to save the model if there are any errors.
		The <bold>Database File Info</bold> tab provides a brief database summary of the selected model in the "Database" panel. 
		</para>
		</item>

		<item>
		<para><bold>Database panel (Panel D)</bold></para>
		<para>
		This is the bottom left panel in the figure above. This panel allows the viewer to view/select models from different database sources. This panel has the following 3 tabs.
		The <bold>VCell Database</bold> tab shows the models stored in the VCell database. This selection shows another set of 3 tabs (<bold>BioModels</bold>, <bold>MathModels</bold>, <bold>Geometries</bold>), 
		which display the different VCell document types stored in the VCell database. Refer to the section on <link target="VCellDatabase">VCell Database</link> for further information.
		The <bold>BMBD</bold> tab shows models from the <link target="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main/">Biomodels database</link>, a database of annotated published models in SBML that can be imported into the Virtual Cell.
		The <bold>Pathway Commons</bold> tab shows the list of pathways that can be mined from the <bold>Pathway Commons</bold> database. 
		Please refer to sections <link target="PathwayCommonsPanel">Pathway Commons Database</link> and <link target="PathwayOverview">Biological Pathways</link>.
		</para>
		</item>
	</list>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>