<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="File -> Import (BNGL files)" target="ImportBNGL">
	
	<introduction> 
	<para>
	<bold>BNGL</bold> is the <bold>B</bold>io <bold>N</bold>et <bold>G</bold>en <bold>L</bold>anguage that 
	is a native format for storing rule-based models used in BioNetGen and NFSim simulators. VCell supports import of
	models encoded in BNGL. 
	</para>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		<imgReference target = "BNGLImport.gif"/>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>
	To import a file into the Virtual Cell, choose <bold>File -> Import</bold>. This opens a "Choose File" dialog. 
	Navigate to the folder where the file to be imported is stored.
	Click <bold>Open</bold> to import the file or <bold>Cancel</bold> to cancel the operation.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	If some features in BNGL file are not supported by VCell, a pop-up window is launched 
with a suggestion to correct unsupported features.
In some cases, when some features in BNGL file (such as fixed value of concentration) are supported by 
BioNetGen but not NFsim, only a single deterministic rule-based application will be created.
	</para>
	
		<imgReference target = "BNGLDebugger.gif"/>
	
	<para>
	<bold>Unit conversions from SBML</bold>
	</para>
	<para>
	BNGL does not have defined units (units are implicit and must be consistent), while VCell must have a defined unit system.
	During import, a user must define a default substance units for the imported model as either Concentrations or Molecules. 
    Note that Virtual Cell internally represents species and kinetic laws only in terms of concentration, thus 
	every number of molecules is converted to concentration units in the Virtual Cell by dividing 
	the quantity in substance units by the size of the compartment in which the species is located. 
	Also, reaction rates in SBML are defined in terms of substance/time, which are converted to concentration/time 
	while importing into the Virtual Cell.
	</para>
	<list>
		<item> <bold>Concentration</bold>
			<para>
		The user must define a concentration <bold>scale</bold> (Molar, micromolar or nanomolar) for numbers in BNGL file 
			to define concentration units. Default <bold>time</bold> units must be defined as well. 
			</para> 
			<para><bold>Note:</bold> While for BioNetGen application (deterministic), 
			VCell simulation results will be identical to BioNetGen stand-alone simulation results, 
			NFSim or BioNetGen stochastic 
			simulation results depend on the volume set by a user. Suggested volume is 5,000 um3 - a volume of a typical cell, 
			but user must be aware that the number of molecules in such volume may exceed the default 
			200,000 molecules in NFSim simulation parameter - this number can be increased, but at a heavy computational 
			cost. If the volume is set to 1, NFSim simulation results should average to BioNetGen simulation results 
			- unless concentrations are set to be less than one, in which case stochastic simulations will be difgferent.
				</para>
		</item>
		<item> <bold>Molecules</bold>
		<para>
		 The user defines default <bold>time</bold> units, simulation <bold>volume</bold> (the volume of a single compartment 
		 	all species will be placed to) and <bold>volume units</bold>. 
			</para> 
			<para><bold>Note:</bold> For BioNetGen application (deterministic), all units will be converted to 
			concentrations using the provided volume. If volume is set to one, then
			VCell simulation results for either BioNetGen or NFSim applications will be identical 
			to BioNetGen stand-alone simulation results. 		
		</para>
		</item>
	</list>
	</operations>
	<comments>  </comments>

</page>

</vcelldoc>