<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="VisIt Visualization Tool">

	<introduction>
	The <bold>VisIT Visualization Tool</bold> is a separate tool for display/analysis of spatial simulation results based on Lawrence Livermore National laboratory 'VisIt' visualization software.  
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>	
		<imgReference target = "VisitTool.png"/>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>
	Before starting the VisIt tool, open at least 1 VCell BioModel or MathModel containing simulation results you want to display. 
	After selecting Tools->'Launch VisIt-based Visulaization Tool' VCell will try to automatically locate and run the necessary VisIt software on your computer.  
	If VCell cannot locate the VisIt software a dialog will appear asking you to manually locate the installed VisIt software or download VisIt from the 
	Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories at <bold>https://wci.llnl.gov/codes/visit</bold>, follow link <bold>Downloads->Executables</bold> 
	to download and install the latest version of VisIt.
	</para>
	<para>
	Once the VCell VisIt viewer dialog appears start by choosing <bold>File->Load Sim from open VCell Models</bold>.  
	A selection dialog will appear containing a list of simulations from all currently open BioModels/MathModels on your local computer.  
	Select 1 row from the list and click 'Open'.  Once the simulation data has been loaded the VisIt viewer window title will show the model and simulation name you chose.  
	The main parts of the viewer are:
	<list>
	<item><bold>Plot</bold> panel that displays a 3D view of the selected simulation data.</item>
	<item><bold>Variables</bold> list for choosing which simulation variable to display in the plot panel.</item>
	<item><bold>Time</bold> slider for choosing which simulation time point to display.</item>
	<item><bold>Slice</bold> button and slider to activate a cut-plane through the 3D plot view.</item>
	<item><bold>Show Post Processing Statistics</bold> button. (see <link target = "PostProcessingStats">Post Processing Statistics</link>)</item>
	<item><bold>Pick</bold> info area at the bottom of the viewer to display data values clicked in the plot panel with the mouse pointer.</item>
	</list>
	</para>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>