<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<vcelldoc>
<page title="Assignment Rules">

	
	<introduction><bold>Assignment Rules</bold> is an alternate way to define the values of Variables in a model and the relationships between them. 
	<para>The functional form of an Assignment Rule is <bold>x = f(V)</bold> (left hand side is a scalar) where x is the variable, f is an arbitrary function returning a numerical result and V is a vector of symbols that does <bold>not</bold> include x. </para>
	The variable may be a reactant or product species already defined in the reaction network. However, the Species must be <bold>clamped</bold> (in the Specifications / Species panel).
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		<imgReference target= "AssignmentRules.png"/>
	<para></para>
	The Assignment Rules screen is a table with four columns.
	<list>
  	<item><bold>Name</bold> is a user defined name for the rule.</item>
	<item>The <bold>Variable</bold> is the user defined species variable whose value will be determined by the assignment rule expression.  In general the variable should not be a species already described in the reaction network or a predefined variable or constant in VCell. </item>
  	<item><bold>Type</bold> defines the variable type and cannot be edited. Only species variables can be created at this time, however it is possible to also import global parameters</item>
	<item><bold>Expression</bold> is the expression that will be evaluated for define the value of the species variable.</item>	
	</list>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>Create a new</bold> Assignment Rule using the New button at the top of the Assignment Rules window.
	<para>
	<bold>Edit</bold> the Assignment Rule by double clicking within the appropriate column.  
	The user must choose (from a list) a variable name for the <bold>Variable</bold> and enter an appropriate <bold>Expression</bold> for the value of the Variable.
	</para>
	<para>
    The <bold>Name</bold> of the Assignment Rule can also be edited.
	</para>
	
	<para>The Specifications / Species panel has an extra "Rules" column for non-spatial deterministic applications, where we indicate if a species is being used as a rule variable.</para>
	Species used as assignment rule variables must be clamped, otherwise an error will be issued.
	<imgReference target= "SpeciesSpecifications_nonspatial_det.png"/>
	<para>
	In the example above, species <bold>'ad'</bold> is marked with the assignment rule icon and is clamped.
	</para>
	
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>