<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<vcelldoc>
<page title="Rate Rules">

	
	<introduction><bold>Rate Rules</bold> allow a user to define the rate of change of a variable (species) using a specified function, rather than describing a kinetic law in the reaction editor.  This is convenient for many ODE applications, and is also used in many SBML models that are imported into VCell. 
	<para>The functional form of a Rate Rule is <bold>dx/dt = f(W)</bold> (left hand side is a rate of change) where x is the variable, f is an arbitrary function returning a numerical result and W is a vector of symbols that may include x. </para>
	The variable cannot be a reactant or product species already defined in the reaction network, where the math will be defined by the kinetic rate law as part of the reaction diagram. 
	Rather, a rate rule expression defines the rate of change of a variable that can act to catalyze a reaction.
 	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
		<imgReference target= "RateRules.png"/>
	<para></para>
	The Rate Rules screen is a table with four columns.
	<list>
  	<item><bold>Name</bold> is a user defined name for the rule.</item>
	<item>The <bold>Variable</bold> is the user defined species variable whose rate of change (dx/dt) will be determined by the rate rule expression.  In general the variable should not be a species already described in the reaction network or a predefined variable or constant in VCell. </item>
  	<item><bold>Type</bold> defines the variable Type and cannot be edited.  In VCell, a new "species" is created in the math description for the variable, and the value of the variable will be reported in the results as a species concentration.</item>
	<item><bold>Expression</bold> is the expression that will be evaluated for define the value of the variable (species).</item>	
	</list>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>Create a new</bold> Rate Rule using the New button at the top of the Rate Rules window.
	<para>
	<bold>Edit</bold> the Rate Rule by double clicking within the appropriate column.  
	The user must choose (select from a list) a species for the <bold>Variable</bold> and enter an appropriate <bold>Expression</bold> for the rate of change.
	</para>
	<para>
    The <bold>Name</bold> of the Rate Rule can also be edited.
	</para>
	
	<para></para>
	The Specifications / Species panel has an extra "Rules" column for non-spatial deterministic applications, where we indicate if a species is being used as a rule variable.
	<imgReference target= "SpeciesSpecifications_nonspatial_det.png"/>
	<para>
	In the example above, species <bold>'e'</bold> is marked with the rate rule icon.
	</para>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>