<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Pathway Import Table" target="PathwayImportTable">

	<introduction>
	The pathway import table shows, for an imported pathway, the interactions (i.e. biochemical reaction,
	transport, transport with biochemical reaction) and the physical entities (i.e. proteins, small molecules, complexes,
	DNA, RNA) it contains. 
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "PathwayImportTable.png"/>
	<para>
	Most of the space is occupied by the pathway import table, which shows entities from an imported pathway
	to select those entities that should be added to the pathway model. It has three columns: the first contains
	selection checkboxes, the second an entity name and the third the (BioPAx Level 2) type of entity.
	At the bottom, there is a search text field to filter results and an add button to add selected entities
	to the pathway model.
    </para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	After a pathway is imported, its entities appear in the pathway import table. Selection checkboxes can be used to
	select those entities which should be added to the pathway model. Entering a string into the search text field causes 
	the entity list to be filtered and only those entities to appear which match the search text. 
	The table can be sorted by clicking on a table header.
	<para>
	After entities have been selected, pressing the add button will add these entities to the pathway model, 
	including dependencies (e.g. if adding a reaction, all participants will come along).
	</para>
	<para>
	The pathway model entities are being displayed as a 
	<link target = "PathwayDiagramView"> diagram</link> 
	or as a 
	<link target = "PathwayObjectsView"> table</link> .	
	</para>
	<para>
	The table items can be sorted alphabetically by any column by clicking on the column header. As an added capability,
	the items in the table can be filtered in real time by typing a string inside the Search field. 
	</para>
	<imgReference target = "PathwayImportTableSearch.png"/>
	</operations>	
</page>

</vcelldoc>