<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Geometry Overview">

	<introduction>
There are 2 types of geometries in VCell, <bold>spatial</bold> and <bold>non-spatial</bold>: 
<list>
<item>Non-spatial geometries (0 dimensional and not spatially resolved) are implicitly defined in non-spatial applications (for ODE and non-spatial stochastic simulations).</item>
<item>Spatial geometries (1,2,3 dimensional and spatially resolved) must be explicitly defined by the user in spatial applications (for PDE and spatial stochastic simulations).</item>
</list>
Spatial geometries can be defined in several ways:
<list>
<item>Re-using previously defined geometries from other VCell model applications (including shared models from other users).</item>
<item>Creating new geometries by defining analytic equations that describe compartment distributions in space.  (<link target="geom_Analytic">Analytic Geometry</link>)</item>
<item>Creating new geometries by manually defining compartments on a regular grid of points in space (image painting).  (<link target="geom_from_images">Image Geometry</link>)</item>
<item>Creating new geometries by importing pre-segmented image files defining compartments as areas of different pixel values.  (<link target="geom_from_images">Image Geometry</link>)</item>
<item>Creating new geometries by importing image files as templates and performing image processing functions to define compartments.  (<link target="geom_from_images">Image Geometry</link>)</item>
<item>Creating new geometries by importing surface mesh files and sampling within a spatial domain to define compartments.  (<link target="geom_from_surface">Geometry from Surface</link>)</item>
</list>
Geometries can be viewed as:
<list>
<item>Individual image planes in the x,y,z dimension.</item>
<item>Rendered surface boundaries between compartment regions.</item>
</list>
<link target="Kinematics">Kinematics</link> can be used to specify velocities of spatial objects in applications that employing moving boundaries.  The current moving boundary solver can be used for 2D geometries only.
<para>
The Geometry domain (origin and extent) can be edited. The geometry can be exported in different surface mesh formats by clicking the <bold>Export...</bold> button.  
Analytic geometries functions can be edited in place by double-clicking the table cell containing the analytic expression.
An analytic geometry can be converted to an <link target="geom_from_images">Image Geometry</link> by clicking the <bold>Edit Image</bold> button.
The currently defined geometry can be changed (replaced).  
<imgReference target = "frm_geometry_overview.png"/>
</para>
</introduction>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>