<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    allowable formatting tags:
     
		<link target = "target"> put your link here </link> 
		Note: web link is allowed in target just put web address (it has to start with "http://") in the target attribute value. 
		e.g. <link target = "http://www.copasi.org/tiki-view_articles.php"> COPASI website </link>
		 
		<imgReference target = "target"/>
		
		<def target = "target" label = "Species"> put your link here </def> NOTE: no recursive definition allowed.
	    
	    <bold> </bold>
	    
		<para> </para> NOTE: link element is allowed in the para
		
		<list> <item> </item> ... </list> NOTE: no embeded lists, but <para>, <link> and <imgReference> are allowed in the list. 
		      
    NOTE: introduction is required. 
          Please save your file as ".xml" in to VCell/UserDocumentation/your chapter name.
          Please be noted no space and special chars are allowed in the file name. 
          Please name your target as the file name(you are linking to) without extension. (e.g to set a link to Phys_Struct.html, you write target = "Phys_Struct"). 
          Before you commit, please try it out in browser first.
		  
		  Image formatting:
		  image size must be no larger than 600*600. Otherwise please create both thumbnail image and original image and use thumbnail syntex.
		  
		  
-->
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Structure Mapping for non-spatial geometries" target="geom_nonspatial_mapping">

	
	<introduction>
	Compartmental BioModel structure mapping (to an empty geometry) is created automatically. 
	However, it is necessary to define the size (micrometers cubed for volume structures -or- microns squared for membrane structures) of each compartment.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance><imgReference target = "nonspatialStructureMapping.png"/></appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit or Enter</bold> structure volume within the Structure Mapping table in the bottom panel by editing the "Size" column.  
	For help determining appropriate values, select "Volume and Surface Calculator" to bring up a calculator to provide volume and surface area information for common geometries (e.g. sphere or cube) based on radius or side lengths. 
	Click "Volume and Surface Calculator" again to hide the calculator.  (See below for older model non-spatial structure mapping).
	</para>
	<para>
	<bold>Note:</bold>
	If one creates a new non-spatial application by copying a spatial application as nonspatial, the equivalent compartment sizes will be pre-computed and automatically entered into the appropriate fields.
	</para>
	<para>
	<bold>Legacy Non-Spatial Structure Mapping:</bold>
	  VCell models previously used surface to volume ratios and volume fractions to describe the compartment sizes, Vcell now uses absolute sizes to describe the sizes of each compartment.  
	For these older models, the values in the "size" column will not exist, enter a size for 1 of the compartments and VCell will automatically calculate the others from the surface to volume ratios and volume factions.  
	Once the size has been entered, the table will report either the size ratio of volume compartment to the parent compartment in which it is contained (volume:volume) column, 
	or the ratio of a membrane compartment surface to the total enclosed volume (surface:volume).  These two columns cannot be edited.
	<imgReference target = "nonspatialLegacyStructureMapping.png"/>
	</para>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>