<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Kinematics">

	<introduction>
Virtual Cell supports moving boundary applications for 2D geometries using a moving boundary solver.  
Specifying a velocity field for objects using the <bold>Kinematics</bold> tab in the Geometry workspace automatically invokes use of the moving boundary solver for simulations. 
Either a constant value or a function can be used to describe the velocity of defined spatial objects within the simulation.
<imgReference target="KinematicsTab.png"/>
	</introduction>

	<appearance>
The kinematics tab in the geometry workspace displays two Tables.
	<para>
The top <bold>Spatial Objects Table</bold> identifies the different spatial objects in the BioModel along with the associated properties that can be used in kinematic expressions for each object.
	<imgReference target="SpatialObjectsTable.png"/>
	<list>
	<item><bold>Volume Objects</bold> are defined by the BioModel structures and can use properties of <bold>centroid, velocity and size</bold>.</item>
	<item><bold>Surface Objects</bold> are defined by the BioModel structures and can use properties of <bold> unit normal, velocity, distance, direction, and size</bold>.</item>
	<item><bold>Point Objects</bold> are defined in the kinematics and can use properties of <bold>position (x and y coordinates), velocity, direction, and distance</bold>.</item>
	</list>
	</para>
	Each type of Object has a Properties Pane that allows the user to select the properties that will be used to define the kinematics.  See the appropriate Properties Pane information for each type of spatial Object.
	<para><bold>Add</bold> a new Point Object in the Spatial Objects table using the <bold>New</bold> button.
	</para>
	<bold>Delete</bold> a selected Point Object in the Spatial Objects table using the <bold>Delete</bold> button.
	<list>
	<item><link target="PP_KinematicsPointObject">Point Object Properties Pane</link></item>
	<item><link target="PP_KinematicsSurfaceObject">Surface Object Properties Pane</link></item>	
	<item><link target="PP_KinematicsVolumeObject">Volume Object Properties Pane</link></item>
	</list>
	</appearance>

	<operations>
The lower <bold>Spatial Process</bold> table defines the movement of objects in the simulation.
	<imgReference target="SpatialProcessTable.png"/>
	<list>
	<item><bold>Point Location Processes</bold> (pproc) define point locations over time (x and y coordinates)</item>
	<item><bold>Point Kinematics</bold> (pproc) is not currently supported</item>
	<item><bold>Surface Kinematics</bold> (sproc) define membrane velocities</item>
	<item><bold>Volume Kinematics</bold> (vproc) define volume velocities</item>
	</list>
	
	<para><bold>Add</bold> a new Spatial Process by first selecting a spatial object and then use the dropdown box in the <bold>New</bold> button in the Spatial Process Table.</para> 
	<bold>Add or Edit</bold> the expression for velocity using the properties enabled for that object. See the Properties Pane information for each type of spatial process. 
	<list>
	<item><link target="PP_KinematicsPointLocationProcess">Point Location</link></item>
	<item><link target="PP_KinematicsSurfaceProcess">Surface Kinematic Process</link></item>	
	<item><link target="PP_KinematicsVolumeProcess">Volume Kinematic Process</link></item>
	</list>
	
	</operations>
</page>

</vcelldoc>