<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reactions Properties Pane" target="PP_Reactions">

  <introduction>
  The reaction properties panel is used to display and edit properties of a reaction, which are the name, the reaction rate J and 
  the math terms involved in J, and a free text annotation.
  </introduction>
		
  <appearance>
  <para>
  On top, there is an editable field for the name of the reaction. One line below that, there is a non-editable combobox
  offering a few options for a reaction rate law, and a conversion button to convert the rate law either from molecules per second to 
  micromolar per second or vice versa.
  </para>
  <para>
  Below these, taking most of the space of the panel, there is the kinetic table of math terms used to define the reaction rate J: 
  the first row contains
  the reaction rate J itself, and further rows contain named mathematical terms referred to by J (e.g. kinetic parameters)
  or referred to by any of the other math terms 
  in the table. If needed, the terms include species concentrations, whose name is the species name. 
  Typically, concentrations of all reactants and catalysts are needed (and products, if reversible).
  </para>
  <para>
  Columns of the kinetic table are: the name, the description, a checkbox whether it is a global expression 
  (i.e. shared across the model,
  as opposed to local, i.e. used only in this reaction), the math expression and the units of measurement.
  </para>
  <para>
  At the bottom, there is a text field for free text annotations, which can be hidden or shown by clicking on on the tiny button 
  left of the "Add Annotation Here" label.
  </para>
  </appearance>
	
  <operations>
    <para>
    The name of the reaction can be changed by editing the text field. A name already given to another reaction will be rejected.
    </para>
    <para>
    The rate law combobox can be used to either select one of a few predefined rate laws 
    (mass action, Michaelis-Menten reversible and irreversible) in micromolar per second or choose to enter a user-defined rate law, 
    either in micromolar per second or in molecules per second. 
    </para>
    <para>
    If the rate law is in micromolar per second, the conversion button will convert it to molecules per second, and vice versa. 
    Note that predefined laws are only in micromolar per second, so if they are converted to molecules per second, they
    will be converted to user-defined, and remain so even if converted back.
    </para>
    <para>
    Expressions and their units can be edited except for predefined rate laws, species concentrations and universal constants. 
    Incompatible units will be silently rejected. 
    If references to new terms are added to expressions of existing ones, new rows will automatically be added for these terms. 
    Each term can be set to global or local by a checkbox, except for the reaction rate, which is always local, and species
    concentrations and universal constants, which are always global. 
    If a term is global, it is identical to any global term of the same name. If a term is
    local, it is different from any term in a different context.
    </para>
    <para>
    The text field for free text annotations can be edited.
    </para>
  </operations>

</page>

</vcelldoc>