<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Entities Management Toolbar" target="GroupOperationsPanel">

	<introduction>
The buttons shown in this toolbar allow the user to perform various useful operations 
on selected entities within the 
		<link target = "PathwayDiagramView">Pathway Diagram</link> view
and the 
		<link target = "PathwayObjectsView">Pathway Objects</link> table view.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
This toolbar shows buttons allowing group, delete and link operations on selected 
entities. A <bold>Search</bold> feature filters entities by string.
		<imgReference target = "OperationsToolbar.png"/>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
The user can perform various operations upon these entities, either on individually selected 
entities or multiple selected entities.
<para></para>
<bold>Importing.</bold> Single / multiple pathway entities can be imported into Physiology. 
Following this process, new species and/or reactions will be created within the BioModel. A permanent
link will preserve the relationship between the BioModel and the Pathway entities. 
To do this, select one or more pathway
entities and press the <bold>Physiology Links</bold> button, then use the option <bold>Import into physiology...</bold>
In the Dialog box the user is allowed to edit the 
values for the compartment, ID and stoichiometric coefficient. The Location/Compartment column provides the drop-down list of compartments specified in Physiology.
If no compartments are specified, it shows the default compartment c0. In the 
example below, the reactants are located in c1 while the product is located on the membrane. 
The reaction itself must be treated as a membrane reaction because at least one reaction participant 
is located on the membrane. ID is the name that will be assigned to the species or reaction in the Physiology.
		<imgReference target = "PathwayImportDlg.png"/>
<para></para>
Once that step is finished the imported entities are displayed within the 
		<link target = "ReactDiagView"> Reaction Diagram View</link> 
		and show a small 'L' mark inside nodes, indicating their linked status. 
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramLinkedComp.png"/>
<para></para>
Returning to the Pathway Diagram View it can be noticed that the linked entities display a 
small 'L' mark within their circle representation, indicating their linked status.
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramLinked1.png"/>
<para></para>

<bold>Editing Physiology Links.</bold> The user can link/unlink every pathway object to every object in the physiology (reactions or species).
Selecting <bold>Physiology Links -> Edit Physiology Links...</bold> will start a dialog box with the list of all objects that can be linked
(species for a physical entity or reactions for an interaction). The user can create new links or deleted existing links by checking/unchecking 
checkboxes in the dialog. The search field is provided for easy filtering.
		<imgReference target = "PhysiologyEditLinks.png"/>

<para></para>
<bold>Grouping.</bold> Selecting multiple entities either 
in a <link target = "PathwayDiagramView">Pathway Diagram</link> view or in a 
<link target = "PathwayObjectsView">Pathway Objects</link> view 
enables a <bold>Group</bold> button. 
Grouping reduces clutter and allows the user to focus on the significant parts of the view. Consider 
the view below:
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramLinked1.png"/>

<para></para>
The user may choose to group all the linked items (those marked with a 'L' letter) under a group 
and all the participants of the other reaction under a second group. The entities can be selected 
either in a <link target = "PathwayDiagramView">Pathway Diagram</link> view or in a 
<link target = "PathwayObjectsView">Pathway Objects</link> view.  The result will look as 
follows: 
		<imgReference target = "PathwayGroupedItems.png"/>
<para>
Existing groups can be grouped in even larger groups. Also groups can be broken down into 
their original subcomponents using the Ungroup option.
</para><para>
<bold>Deleting.</bold> Single / multiple entities can be deleted from the view using the <bold>Delete Selected</bold> button. Note 
that linked entities cannot be deleted as long as the link exists. In the case of selections 
where some entities can be deleted and some others can not, a warning dialog box will display 
pertinent information. In the example below the user tried to delete two reactions one of which 
is linked.
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDeleteObjectDlg.png"/>
</para>	

</operations>
</page>

</vcelldoc>