<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Molecules Properties Pane" target="PP_Molecules">

	<introduction>
	The Molecules Properties Pane includes a graphical editor used to specify sites within <link target = "Molecules">Molecules</link> using drop-menus that appear upon right mouse click in the 
		<bold>Object Properties</bold> pane. An annotation box is also provided.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>Rename</bold> a site or <bold>add</bold> a new site using the right mouse button to click on the molecule shape and select from the drop-down menu.
		<imgReference target = "PP_BNG_Molecules_new.png"/>

	<para>
<bold>Add a state </bold>to a site,<bold> move</bold> or <bold>rename</bold> a site by right click on molecule site and selecting from the drop-down menu.
		<imgReference target = "PP_BNG_Molecules.png"/></para>

	<para>
	<bold>Anchor</bold> the molecule to a particular compartment or compartments within the physiology using the radio buttons in the <bold>Anchor Molecule</bold> region of the Properties Pane.
	<list>
		<item><bold>No restrictions</bold> places no restrictions on where the molecular type can exist; the molecule can participate in reactions with other molecules in any compartment.  When a molecule with no restrictions binds to a molecule in a different compartment, the product molecule will reside within the compartment where the reaction occurs.
		</item>
		<item><bold>Structure Name</bold> selects compartments where the molecule is anchored.  Anchoring to a compartment or compartments prevents the molecule from participating in reactions that do not occur within the selected compartment(s).</item>
	</list>
		Anchoring prevents unwanted reactions from occurring, e.g. to prevent a membrane molecule from becoming a soluble molecule by binding to a cytosolic or extracellular molecule. Note that two molecules that do not share an anchored compartment cannot interact with each other.  For example, a molecule anchored (restricted) to the membrane cannot bind to a molecule anchored (restricted) to the cytosol.  The molecule in the cytosol must either have no anchoring restrictions or be anchored to both the membrane and the cytosol to participate in a reaction with a membrane-anchored molecule, and the reaction occurs in the membrane compartment.  The product of the binding reaction in this example becomes a membrane-anchored molecule.  Note that multiple anchors can be applied, but caution is advised as this can lead to unexpected results.
	</para>
	</operations>	
</page>

</vcelldoc>