<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Problems (Issues) Panel" target="PP_Problems">

	<introduction>
The Problems Tab within the Properties pane provides errors and warnings identified by VCell. 		
	</introduction>

	<appearance>
	Below is an example of problems of various severities, two of which are Errors and the other five are Warnings.
	<para>
	The first column of the table describes the nature of the problem, the second gives the name of the entity involved (entities may be species, 
	reaction, kinetic parameters, structures, a.s.o.). The third column describes to location where the problem occurred (for example in the Physiology / Reactions 
	table or an Application-specific problem in the Species / Specifications panel).
    </para>
	<imgReference target = "ProblemPanel.png"/>
	<imgReference target = "PP_ProblemsIcon.png"/> 
	This icon indicates errors that are serious enough to render your BioModel inconsistent.  
	All <bold>errors</bold> must be <bold>corrected</bold> before a BioModel can be <bold>saved.</bold>
 	</appearance>

	<operations>
	<para>
	Double clicking on a problem (for example the one highlighted in the image above) will open the panel where the problem occurred and place the 
	selection on the entity involved. In this example it is an attribute of a species belonging to a 3D stochastic application.
    </para>
   	<imgReference target = "ProblemExample.png"/>
   	<para>
	The Problems Panel is not the only way to identify problems. Each table will display a small Error or Warning icon next to the entity involved. 
	A colored border will also be drawn around the table row of the entity, red for Errors and orange for Warnings.
    </para>
   	<para>
	Finally, hovering the mouse cursor over such an icon will open a tool tip window which a description of the problem and sometimes with 
	suggestions about a possible fix.
    </para>
   	<imgReference target = "ProblemToolTip.png"/>
	<para>
	See the <link target = "Errors"> Errors List </link> or <link target = "WarningsList"> Warnings List </link> for additional explanations. 			
	</para>	
	</operations>

</page>

</vcelldoc>