<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reactions Properties Pane" target="PP_Reactions">

  <introduction>
  The reaction properties panel is used to display and edit properties of a reaction.
  </introduction>
		
  <appearance>
  <imgReference target = "PP_Reactions.png"/>
  <para>
  The top of the table shows the Reaction Name,a combobox for Kinetic Type, and a button to convert the rate law either from molecules per 
  second to micromolar per second or vice versa. Below is a table of the kinetic terms used to define the reaction rate 
  (J)that includes all mathematical terms referred to in the mathematical expression for J or other kinetic terms.  Concentrations 
  of all species referred to in the kinetic terms (e.g.reactants, catalysts, products)are required. Items in brown cannot be edited.
  </para>
  </appearance>
	
  <operations>
    <para>
    <bold>Edit the reaction name</bold> using the text field. A name already given to another reaction will be rejected.
    </para>
    <para>
    <bold>Select a rate law</bold> using the combobox to select one of a few predefined rate laws 
    (mass action, Michaelis-Menten reversible and irreversible) in micromolar per second or to enter a user-defined 
    rate law, either in micromolar per second or in molecules per second. 
    </para>
    <para>
    <bold>Convert the rate law</bold> from micromolar per second to molecules per second, or vice versa, using the 
    <bold>Convert to</bold> button. Note that predefined laws are only in micromolar per second, so if they are converted 
    to molecules per second, the user-defined kinetic law will automatically be selected, and remain so even if converted back.
    </para>
    <para>
    <bold> Edit Expressions and their units</bold> in the Expression column.  
    <list>
    <item>Predefined rate laws, species concentrations and universal constants cannot be edited.</item> 
    <item>Incompatible units will be silently rejected.</item> 
    <item>If references to new terms are added, new rows will automatically be added for these terms.  An expression for each new
    term must be added in the expression column</item> 
    <item>Terms can be set to <def target = "def_Global">global</def> or <def target = "def_Local">local</def> using a 
    checkbox, except for the reaction rate, which is always local.  Species concentrations and universal constants 
    are always global.</item> 
	</list>
	
    <bold> Add Annotations</bold> in the Annotation text field, which can be shown or hiddenby selecting the plus or minus 
    sign next to the <bold>Add Annotation Here</bold>.text.  Annotations apply to the entire reaction.
    </para>
  </operations>

</page>

</vcelldoc>