<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reactions Rules Editor Pane" target="PP_ReactionRulesEditor">

  <introduction>
  The reaction rules editor pane is currently the only way to specify and edit a reaction rule.
  <imgReference target = "PP_ReactionRules.png"/>
  </introduction>
		
  <appearance>
  	Each reaction rule is specified on two lines, with reactants on the firsl line and products underneath. This way a modeler
  	can easily see the transformation of reactants to products. 
  Sites in white are fully unspecified (they can be bound or unbound, denoted by grey question mark under the site). 
  	Sites in green must have either binding status defined 
  	(bound to specific site - denoted by color bond with index, bound to arbitrary site - denoted by vertical line , unbound), 
  	or state defined. The first rule describes binding of egfr monomer (site r is unbound) to free egf (site r is unbound).
  	The second rule describes phosphorylation of unbound Y1148 site (change of state from Y to P) on a receptor that is bound to
  	another receptor (site r is bound) but may be bound to a ligand (question mark under l site) and 
  	site Y1068 may be in any state and may be either bound or not.
  	  <imgReference target = "RR_00.PNG"/>
  </appearance>
	
<operations>
	<bold>Reaction Rule edit/specification:</bold>
		<list>
			<item>Right click mouse on the first shape to select the first molecule for the first reactant.
			<imgReference target = "RR_1.PNG"/></item>
			<item>To add more reactants, right click on the empty space next to reaction arrow: 			
			<imgReference target = "RR_2.PNG"/></item>
			<item>To specify reactant or product consisting of multiple molecules, right click next to the existing molecule.
			<imgReference target = "RR_3.PNG"/></item>
			<item>Specify how molecules are connected by mouse right click on binding site shape. All changes on reactants are propagated 
				to products:
			<imgReference target = "RR_4.PNG"/></item>
			<item>Specify explicit bonds by mouse right click on state shape. Changes in products do not propagate to reactions.
			<imgReference target = "RR_5.PNG"/></item>
		</list>

		<para><bold>Note:</bold> If reaction rule has multiple identical molecules, they are enumerated to provide 
		one-to-one mapping from reactants to products. The match is established automatically, but can be reassigned
		with a right click on a molecular shape.
		<imgReference target = "RulesMatch.PNG"/></para>
		
	</operations>

</page>

</vcelldoc>