<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Pathway Commons Database" target="PathwayCommonsPanel">

	<introduction>
	<para>
	The <bold>Pathway Commons</bold> panel allows to query and download biological pathways from Pathway Commons in BioPAX Level 2.
	Pathway Commons aggregates and integrates the content of nine major pathway databases (BioGRID, MSKCC Cancer Cell Map,
	Human Protein Database, HumanCyc, SBCNY IMID, IntAct, MINT, NCI/Nature PID, Reactome). 
	As of October 2011, Pathway Commons contains 1,623 pathways, 585,237 interactions, 105,949 physical entities and 564 organisms.
	Downloaded pathways can be used to build and annotate models based on the pathways and their links to terminologies and databases
	about proteins, small molecules, genes, anatomical features, organisms and publications.
	</para>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "PathwayCommonsPanel.png"/>
	<para>
	The <bold>Search</bold> at the top of the Pathway Commons Panel works as OR for several search terms, 
	and search term is searched inside pathways from Pathways Commons. For every pathway the database and organism are displayed after.
	The <bold>Filter</bold> below search results filters just names of the pathways, it does not check
	the content of pathways. The list of pathways can be filtered by database name or organism, or sorted in alphanumeric order.
	</para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>
	To begin, a search text is entered in the search text field and the <bold>Search</bold> button is pressed to send a request to Pathway Commons.
	The result of this query is a list of pathways in which the search term participates.
	</para>
	<para>
	Each pathway listed in the search results can be selected and then 
	<link target = "PathwayImportTable"> previewed</link> in the VCell
	by pressing the <bold>Preview</bold> button, which will obtain 
	the pathway in BioPAX Level 2 from Pathway Commons. 
	</para>
	<para>
	The <bold>Open Weblink</bold> button will cause the web browser to open the page of Pathway Commons dedicated to that pathway.
	</para>
	</operations>	
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>