<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Pathway Commons Database" target="PathwayCommonsPanel">

	<introduction>
	<para>
	The <bold>Pathway Commons</bold> panel allows to query and download biological pathways from Pathway Commons in BioPAX Level 2.
	Pathway Commons aggregates and integrates the content of nine major pathway databases (BioGRID, MSKCC Cancer Cell Map,
	Human Protein Database, HumanCyc, SBCNY IMID, IntAct, MINT, NCI/Nature PID, Reactome). 
	As of October 2011, Pathway Commons contains 1,623 pathways, 585,237 interactions, 105,949 physical entities and 564 organisms.
	Downloaded pathways can be used to build and annotate models based on the pathways and their links to terminologies and databases
	about proteins, small molecules, genes, anatomical features, organisms and publications.
	</para>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "PathwayCommonsPanel.png"/>
	<para>
	At the top of the Pathway Commons Panel, there is the search text field and the <bold>Search</bold> button. At the bottom, there is
	an <bold>Import Pathway</bold> button and the <bold>Open Weblink</bold> button. All other space is to display the search result tree. After a keyword search
	the search result tree shows physical entities obtained in a query, and for each physical entity, a list of pathways that
	contain it.
    </para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>
	To begin, a search text is entered in the search text field and the <bold>Search</bold> button is pressed to send a request to Pathway Commons.
	The result of this query is a list of physical entities (i.e. proteins, small molecules, DNA, RNA, complexes), and for each of 
	these entities a list of pathways in which they participate.
	</para>
	<para>
	Each pathway listed in the search results can be selected and then 
	<link target = "PathwayImportTable"> downloaded</link> 
	by pressing the <bold>Import Pathway</bold> button, which will obtain 
	the pathway in BioPAX Level 2 from Pathway Commons. 
	</para>
	<para>
	The <bold>Open Weblink</bold> button will cause the web browser to open the page of Pathway Commons dedicated to that pathway.
	</para>
	</operations>	
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>