<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Pathway Links">

	<introduction> Objects in Physiology (species and reactions) and pathway entities in Pathway Model can be linked.
	The linked objects are marked with a letter 'L'.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "ShowPathwayLinks.png"> </imgReference>	
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para>
	Selecting a single species or a single reaction in a Reaction Diagram, Reactions Table View, Structure Diagram or 
	Species Table view enables <bold>Pathway Links</bold> button.
	</para><para> 
	If a species or reaction is already linked to a pathway object, 
	there are multiple ways to see <bold>Linked pathways objects</bold>.
	<list>
	<item>double click on blue underlined link that appears in the <bold>Link</bold> columns in <bold>Reactions</bold> 
	and <bold>Species</bold> table views, under <bold>Linked Pathway Objects</bold> in <bold>Reaction Diagram</bold> view
	Annotations and Pathway in Reaction and Species <bold>Object Properties</bold>. </item>
	<item>Select <bold>Show Linked Pathway Objects</bold> under <bold>Pathway Links</bold>menu</item>
	</list>
	As a result, the user will be transfered to <link target = "PathwayDiagramView">Pathway Diagram</link> view where
	linked objects will be shown in red. 
	<imgReference target = "LinkedPathwayObject.png"> </imgReference>
	</para>
	<para>
	
	<bold>Editing Pathway Links.</bold> The user can link/unlink every species and reaction to an 
	every physical entity and interaction in Pathway model.
Selecting <bold>Pathway Links -> Edit Pathway Links...</bold> will start a dialog box with the list of 
all objects that can be linked
(physical entities for a species or interactions for a reaction). The user can create new links or deleted existing links by checking/unchecking 
checkboxes in the dialog. As usual, Search field is provided for easy filtering.
		<imgReference target = "PathwayEditLinks.png"></imgReference>	
		</para>
	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>