<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reactions Diagram View" target="ReactDiagView">

	<introduction> 
	The reaction diagram shows a bipartite graph of species (green balls) and reactions (yellow squares), each placed into their
	compartments, and connected by lines showing which species participates in which reaction.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance> 
	<para>
	<imgReference target = "ReactDiagView.png"/>
	The compartments are shown as a row of white rectangles before a gray background, connected into one large rectangle. 
	Species are green balls and reactions are yellow squares placed into the compartments. Lines each connect one 
	species with one reaction in which it participates: solid lines with arrows denote reactants and products, distinguished by
	the direction of the arrow. Dashed lines denote catalysts. Stoichiometric coefficients, if different from one, are displayed
	next to the appropriate lines.
	</para>
	<para>
	The toolbar on top of the graph shows the following groups of buttons (from left to right): first the select mode button, then
	a group of graph element buttons (species, reactant/product, catalyst), then the group of zoom buttons (in, out) and then a
	group of automatic layout buttons (random, circular, anneal, level, relax, generic logic).
	</para>
	<para>
	The toolbar at the bottom of the graph contains (left to right): a search text field, a delete button and a pathway links button.
	</para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations> 
	<para>
	The mode buttons switch between different modes, each with a different set of available mouse operations:
	  <list>
	    <item>
	    In <bold>selection mode</bold>, graph nodes and edges can be selected and de-selected. Select a single element 
	    by mouse click. Mouse drag selects all graph nodes within a rectangular area spanned by the drag. Mouse clicks while 
	    holding the shift key add elements to the selection. Mouse clicks while holding the control key toggles selection of elements.
	    </item>
	    <item>
	    In <bold>species creation mode</bold>, new species can be created by mouse click. Preliminary names for species are generated
	    automatically, but can be changed immediately in the species property panel.
	    </item>
	    <item>
	    In <bold>reactant/product creation mode</bold>, a mouse drag can be used to assign 
	    reactant or product roles by connecting either existing species or reactions or by creating new ones. The direction of the drag
	    determines whether reactant or product role is assigned (e.g. dragging from species to reaction creates a reactant role, 
	    while the reverse direction creates a product role). The action is subject to constraints (e.g. a reaction in a feature 
	    can not have participants on a membrane) and does nothing if constraints would be violated.
	    Dragging across a membrane creates a flux if it is from species to 
	    empty space, 
	    or the reverse, or form empty space to empty space, or between two species known to be of the same type (this feature
	    may disappear). Otherwise, dragging from species to species or reaction to reaction
	    creates an intermediary reaction or species, respectively; and dragging between a species or reaction and empty space creates
	    a reaction or species respectively.
	    </item>
	    <item>
	    In <bold>catalyst creation mode</bold>, a mouse drag can be used to assign a catalyst role by connecting a species 
	    and a reaction. The direction is irrelevant. Connecting a species with empty space creates a new reaction and vice versa.
	    </item>
	    <item>
	    The <bold>zoom in</bold> and <bold>zoom out</bold> buttons vary the magnification of the diagram.
	    </item>
	    <item>
	    The <bold>layout buttons</bold> perform automatic layout which means each node will be assigned a new position. 
	    The left-most places each node randomly, the next places nodes in an ellipse within each compartment. The fourth
	    tries to arrange nodes in a way that most lines point downwards. The others are more complex, but generally tend to make lines
	    shorter and more similar to each other in lengths and nodes more evenly places across the compartments.
	    </item>
      </list>
	</para>
	<para>
	The <bold>search text field</bold> allows to type a search string and cause those elements to be selected which have attributes
	that match the search string.
	</para>
	<para>
	The <bold>delete button</bold> deletes selected elements, if possible. Delete can fail if other objects depends on
	objects to be deleted (e.g. you can not delete a species if it participated in a reaction, unless you delete the reaction first).
	</para>
	<para>
	The <bold>pathway links button</bold> allows to follow links form model elements (species, reactions) to pathway elements or to 
	edit these links.
    </para>
  </operations>
	
  <properties>
    <para>
    Depending on the type of object selected, the bottom pane of the window displays a 
    <link target = "PP_Reactions">reaction</link>, 
    <link target = "PP_MemFlux">structure</link>, 
    <link target = "PP_Stoichiometries">stoichiometry</link>, 
    <link target = "PP_Species">species</link> or
    <link target = "PP_Structure">structure</link> properties pane 
    </para>
  </properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>