<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Observables Properties Pane" target="PP_Observables">

	<introduction>
	The observables properties tree on a left allows editing of the Observable name, 
	adding/editing/deleting sites and site states. Right pane is uneditable and provides real-time updates 
	of the observable composition.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "PP_BNG_Observables_2.png"/>
	<list>
	<item>Each Observable consists of one or more <bold>Species Patters</bold> that 
	define common features of species selected by Observable.</item>
	<item>Each SpeciesPattern consists of one or more of Molecules (connected through explicit bonds). </item>
	<item>Sites that have specified state are shown in green with state shown
	underneath the site shape.</item> 
	<item>Sites may have defined binding - they can be explicitly bound to another site, 
	declared unbound or declared bound to unspecified site - then the site is shown in green with bond (if exists) 
	shown in solid color.</item>
	<item>Site than can be in any state and can be bound or unbound is shown in white, with possible bond shown 
	in grey as a question mark.</item>
	</list>
	The Observables Tab displays a table of the Observable name, Cartoon depiction of each observable, the 
	<def target = "def_BioNetGen"> BioNetGen </def> definition and what Observable counts.   
	Selecting Observable brings the <link target = "PP_Observables">Observable Properties</link> 
	in the bottom right pane, where a user can specify and edit a selected <bold>Observable</bold>. 
	The composition of Observable is the following:
	<list>
	<item>Each Observable consists of one or more <bold>Species Patters</bold> that 
	define common features of species selected by Observable.</item>
	<item>Each SpeciesPattern consists of one or more of Molecules (connected through explicit bonds) 
	with some sites having specified state values. </item>
	<item>Sites that have specified state value are shown in green.</item> 
	<item>Sites that are explicitly bound to another site, 
	declared unbound or bound are shown in green with bond (if exists) shown in solid color.</item>
	<item>Sites than can be in any state and can be bound or unbound are shown in white.</item>
	<item>Sites that have possible multiple states have yellow sign above site shape.</item>
	</list>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<list>
	<item>Observable name: Right click to add Species Pattern (species with a given set of features).</item>
	<item>Species Pattern: Right click to delete Pattern or Add Molecules that constitute pattern.</item>
	<item>Molecule is added with all sites being in unspecified state (white). Right click on a 
	site to choose a state and specify bond - a site can be connected to any other site in a species pattern, 
	or be declared bound or unbound.</item>
	</list>
	</operations>	

</page>

</vcelldoc>