<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Observable Properties Pane" target="PP_Observables">

	<introduction>The <link target = "Observables">Observables</link> are specified and edited using mouse right click in the bottom 
		<bold>Object Properites</bold> pane. Only annotation can be typed in.	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
  	<list>
  	<item>Each Observable consists of one or more <bold>Species Patters</bold>. Observable selects species that match at least one
	of the species patterns (not both).</item> 
	<item>Each species pattern defines common features of species. It consists of one 
	or more of <link target = "Molecules">molecules</link> that compose
	species. Molecules may or may not be explicitely connected, but must be present 
	in every species selected by this species pattern.</item>
	<item> Sites that have possible multiple states have yellow sign above site shape. 
	Each molecule within species pattern may have some sites being undefined. If site  
	does not have defined states (if states are possible) and its binding is not important, it is shown in white.
	Sites may have defined binding - they can be declared to be explicitly bound to another site, 
	declared unbound or declared bound to "some" (unspecified) site - then the site is shown in green with bond (if exists) 
	shown in solid color. </item>
	<item>Observable below describes the total phosphorylation of all EGFR molecules. The first species pattern selects all
		species that have Y1068 being phosphorylated, the second - all species that have Y1148 phosphorylated.</item>
	</list>
  	  <imgReference target = "O0.PNG"/>
  </appearance>
	
<operations>
	<bold>Observable specification</bold>
		<list>
			<item>Right click mouse on the shape to select the first molecule for the first species pattern.
			<imgReference target = "O1.PNG"/></item>
			<item>Right click on molecular site or state will allow editing. Right click next to molecule will add another molecule. 			
			<imgReference target = "O2.PNG"/></item>
			<item>To add another species patter, right click below the first.
			<imgReference target = "O3.PNG"/></item>
			<item>Similarly to the first species pattern, clicking on shape will allow selection of molecule:
			<imgReference target = "O4.PNG"/></item>
			<item>The second species patter is edited through right click on site and state.
			<imgReference target = "O5.PNG"/></item>
		</list>
	</operations>

</page>

</vcelldoc>