<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Species Properties Pane" target="PP_Species">

	<introduction>
	Selecting a species in the <link target = "ReactDiagView">Reaction Diagram</link> or the <link target = "SpeciesTabView">Species</link> will activate the Species Properties pane in the lower right quadrant of the workspace.  Within this pane, the Species Name can be editing, <link target="PathwayOverview">Linked Pathway Object(s)</link> are displayed, and annotations cans be added.    	
<para> For rule-based models, the <bold>Object Properties</bold> tab provides a graphical editor to specify and edit the molecular details of <link target = "SpeciesTabView">Species</link> using drop-down menus. </para>

	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
			<imgReference target = "PP_CompositeSpecies_defined.PNG"/>		
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	
	<bold>Specify a molecule</bold> previously created in the <link target = "Molecules">Molecules Table</link> as a component of a species in a rule-based model.<para></para>
			<imgReference target = "PP_CompositeSpecies_start.PNG"/>
			<imgReference target = "PP_CompositeSpecies_new.PNG"/>

	<para><bold>Add additional species information</bold>.  When a molecule is added, if additional information is required the species will be highlighted in red and errors may appear in the <link target = "PP_Problems">Problems tab</link>. In the figure shown, three errors were identified. Two errors arise from the fact that two binding sites have unspecified states; one error arises because molecules within the species are not connected with a bond.</para>
			<imgReference target = "PP_CompositeSpecies_error.PNG"/>
	<para>
	</para>
	<para><bold>Specify connections</bold> between molecules in the species by right click on binding site shape and selecting from the drop-down menu</para>
			<imgReference target = "PP_CompositeSpecies_bond1.PNG"/>
	<para>
	</para>
			
	<para><bold>Specify states</bold> for binding sites by mouse right click on state shape and selecting the cognate binding site.  In the figure shown, the number of errors is now one; bounds between molecules are specified connected and 
				only one site has unspecified states.</para>
			<imgReference target = "PP_CompositeSpecies_site.PNG"/>

	</operations>	

</page>

</vcelldoc>