<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Pathway Diagram View" target="PathwayDiagramView">

	<introduction>
Displays in a graphical form the entities selected by the user in the Pathway Panel. It 
can be used to examine their properties, import them within the model and manage their 
link status with model entities.
<para></para>
It is the graph format representation of the 
		<link target = "PathwayObjectsView"> Pathway Objects View</link>
.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
The view represents various entity types as circles and the relationships between them as 
full or dotted lines. The screenshot below shows two biochemical reactions and their 
dependent entities.
<para></para>
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramView.png">
		</imgReference>
<para></para>
The bottom pane of the window displays a 
		<link target = "PP_Pathways"> Pathway Object Properties Pane </link> 
where the properties of a selected entity are being displayed.
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
The user can perform various operations upon these entities, either on individually selected 
entities or multiple selected entities.
<para></para>
More entities can be added from the Pathway Panel.
<para></para>
Single / multiple entities can be deleted from the view.
<para></para>
Multiple entities can be grouped together under a Group entity.
<para></para>
Single / multiple entities can be imported within a model. To do this select one or more 
entities and press the Physiology Links button, then the option Import into physiology...
<para></para>
The Import into physiology Dialog box is opened. Here the user is allowed to edit the 
default values for the compartment and stoichiometric coefficient. Once that step is finished 
the imported entities are displayed within the 
		<link target = "ReactDiagView"> Reaction Diagram View</link>
.
<para></para>
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramLinked2.png">
		</imgReference>
<para></para>
Returning to the Pathway Diagram View it can be noticed that the linked entities display a 
small 'L' mark within their circle representation, indicating their linked status.
<para></para>
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramLinked1.png">
		</imgReference>
<para></para>
	</operations>
</page>

</vcelldoc>