<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Pathway Diagram View" target="PathwayDiagramView">

	<introduction>
Displays in a graphical form the entities imported by the user 
from the <link target = "PathwayImportTable">Pathway Preview</link> panel. It 
can be used to examine their properties, import entities into physiology and manage their 
linking to species and reactions in Physiology.
<para>
<bold>Pathway Diagram</bold> represents graphically objects from the
		<link target = "PathwayObjectsView">Pathway Objects</link> panel.
</para>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
Various physical entities and interactions are shown as circles of different colors 
(brown for complexes, blue for small molecules, green for proteins and others).
The relationships between entities are shown as full lines (for biochemical reactions) 
or dotted lines 9for catalysis and control). Entity names are shortened. 
Mouse over entity gives the full entity name.
		<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramView.png">
		</imgReference>
<para>
Selecting a single entity activates the bottom 
<link target = "PP_Pathways">Entity Properties</link> pane 
that shows the properties of a selected entity.
</para>
	</appearance>
	<operations>
More entities can be added from the 
		<link target = "PathwayImportTable"> Pathway Preview</link>.
		<para>
		Selecting multiple entities activates 
		<link target = "GroupOperationsPanel"> Group</link> button.
		</para>
		<para>
		Selected entities can be imported into the BioModel and be either created new or linked to existing
		species and reactions in Physiology 
		using <link target = "GroupOperationsPanel">Physiology Links</link> button. The same functionality  
		can be accessed as well by mouse right click an entity in the diagram view.
		</para>
<para>		
To simplify operations, the items in the diagram can be filtered in real time by typing a string 
inside the <bold>Search</bold> field. All the matching entities will show up in the diagram as selected 
(marked in red).
	<imgReference target = "PathwayDiagramSearch.png"/>
	</para>
	</operations>
</page>
</vcelldoc>