<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Observables Table" target="Observables">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Observables</bold> are used to specify the outputs of a model; they are functions of the
	total population of multiple species that share a set of properties. For example, to
	simulate the tyrosine phosphorylation level of a particular protein, the
	<bold>Observable</bold> would be a function describing the total amount of all species containing 
	the phosphorylated form of the protein.  
	<list>
	<item>Each Observable consists of one or more <bold>Species Patterns</bold>. Each observable selects species that match at least one of the species patterns (not both). </item>
	<item>A species pattern defines common features of multiple species, and consists of one 
	or more of the <link target = "Molecules">molecules</link> that compose a species. Molecules may or may not be explicitely connected, but must be present in every species selected by the species pattern. Sites that have multiple possible states are depicted with a small yellow ball above the site. </item>
	<item>Each molecule within a species pattern may have sites left undefined. If a site does not have defined states (where states are possible) and the site can be in the bound or unbound state, the site is colored white.</item>
	<item>An observable may identify sites with a defined binding state - i.e. the funciton can explicitly identify a site bound to another site, a site unbound, or a site bound to an unspecified (i.e. any other) site; in this case the site is colored green with a bond drawn as a colored line if one exists.</item>
	<item> A site that has a defined state is always shown in green.</item>
	</list>
		<imgReference target = "observables.PNG"> </imgReference>
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>

		The Observables Table displays 
		<list>
			<item>The <bold>Name</bold> of Observable (can be edited).</item>
			<item>The <bold>Structure</bold> indicates where the species selected by an Observable are located .</item>
			<item>The <bold>Depiction</bold> of each Observable. Green circles within each molecular shape denote 
			molecular sites, small yellow circles denote that this site has possible states. </item> 
			<item>A <def target = "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> definition.  The definition cannot be edited but can be searched.</item>
			<item> The <bold>Count</bold> of either <bold>Molecules</bold> or <bold>Species</bold>. The count of molecules is a <bold>weighted</bold> sum of the population levels of all the species that match the pattern(s) defined in the observable. Each amount is multiplied by the number of times that the species is matched by the pattern(s). For example, a species that consists of two instances of a receptor (i.e. a dimer) is counted twice.
			The count of species is an <bold>unweighted</bold> sum of
			the amounts the species that match the pattern(s) define by the observable. 
			For example, a species that has two instances of a receptor is counted once.</item> 
		</list>	
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> an Observable name within the table.  Note that the function defined by the observable and its properties must be specified in the <link target = "PP_Observables">Observables Properties</link> pane. 
    </para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of observables using the Search Box to enter a name or any part of the observable composition.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> an observable by selecting and using the "Delete" button below the table.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the observable within the <link target = "PP_Observables"> 
	Observable Properties pane </link>.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
