<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Reactions Table" target="ReactTabView">

	<introduction>
	A table of reactions can be used to create and edit <def target = "def_reactions">reactions</def>, 
	membrane fluxes and <def target = "def_ReactionRules">reaction rules</def>.
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>

	The Reactions table has several columns:
	<list> 
		<item>The <bold>Reaction</bold> column lists either a reaction (or flux) that can be edited in place, 
		or "Reaction Rule" text that cannot be edited.</item> 
		<item><bold>Name</bold> lists the reaction name; reaction names are generated automatically as "r_number" but can be edited to any text (without spaces).</item> 
		<item><bold>Structure</bold> lists the <def target = "def_structure">structure</def> where the reaction, flux or reaction rule occurs.</item>
		<item><bold>Depiction</bold> shows the molecular details of the reactants and products. Species that do not have molecular details are depicted as green balls. For reactions, molecular
		details of species appear only if they are first specified in the <link target = "SpeciesTabView">Species</link> tab. For reaction rules, 
		reactant and product molecular details are specified below in the <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesEditor"> Reaction Rules Properties</link> pane. 
		For species with molecular details, green sites denote that the state of the site is specified in the Reaction Rule (e.g. bound/unbound, phosphorylated/unphosphorylate), white sites are undefined in the Reaction Rule. Yellow sites indicate that multiple states are specified. Names of states of sites are omitted in the table for clarity.</item>
		<item><bold>Kinetics</bold> list the kinetic type for the reaction; select the reaction and edit in the properties pane below. For reaction rules, only Mass Action kinetics are allowed. </item>
		<item><bold>BioNetGen Definition</bold> provides the BioNetGen Language (BNGL) string that encodes the rule. It
			cannot be edited but can be searched.</item>
		<item><bold>Links</bold> show links to pathway items (see <link target="PathwayOverview">Biology Pathways</link>); double click on that link to navigate to the Pathway Diagram. 
		A text bubble icon indicates the presence of annotations for the current selection in the <link target ="PP_Annotations">Annotations</link> Properties Panel.</item>
	</list> 
	Below the table are buttons to create or delete reactions or rules, to duplicate reaction rules, define Pathway Links and to search the reaction table.  
	Note that buttons related to Reaction Rules only appear if <def target="def_molecules">Molecules</def> have been created in the model.
		<imgReference target = "Mix_Rules.PNG"/>
		 
	 <para>The bottom pane of the window displays a <link target = "PP_Reactions">Reaction Properties pane</link>,
	<link target = "PP_MemFlux"> Membrane Flux Properties pane</link>, 
	or <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesEditor"> Reaction Rules Properties pane</link>, depending on the current selection. </para>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>New Reaction</bold> calls a popup menu to add a new reaction or flux. Select the structure where the reaction occurs from the Structure drop-down menu, define a name for the reaction and type the reaction using the format "a+b->c" where a and b, etc. are reactants and c, etc are products. Numbers before a species name are used to indicate stoichiometry.  If a, b, etc have not been defined, they are automatically created as species within the structure where the reaction occurs.

		<imgReference target = "RxnAdd2.png"/>
	<para><bold>New Rule</bold> opens the <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesEditor">reaction rule editor</link> in the properties pane below.  New rules must be created and edited within the Editor.</para>
		
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> kinetic laws by selecting a row 
	in the table and editing the <link target = "PP_Reactions"> Reaction Properties pane</link>,  
	<link target = "PP_MemFlux"> Flux Properties pane</link> or <link target = "PP_ReactionRulesEditor">Rule Editor</link> as appropriate.</para>
	<para><bold>Add or Edit Annotations</bold> using the <link target= "PP_Annotations">Annotations</link> tab in the Properties Pane.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> a reaction, flux or rule by selecting a row or rows.</para> 
	<para><bold>Duplicate</bold> will create an exact copy of highlighted rule 
		with a new name "oldname_0".</para> 
	<para> Use the <link target = "PathLink"> Pathway Links</link> button to identify reactions within 
	<def target = "def_pathcom"> Pathway Commons</def> Database.  Pathway Links are not available for reaction rules at this time.</para>
	<para> <bold>Search</bold> the list of reactions and reaction rules using the Search Box 
		to enter reaction name, structure, or any part of a BNGL string.</para>
	</operations>

</page>

</vcelldoc>