<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Species Table" target="SpeciesTabView">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Species</bold> are used to create variables (molecular species) in <def target = "def_reactions">reactions</def> and fluxes and can exist in both <def target = "def_membranes">  membranes </def> and 
 	<def target = "def_compartments"> volume compartments </def> (volumes). 
 	Species are unique pools of molecules within a single structure; if the same species is copied to a different 
 	structure, the structure name is appended to the species name to retain a unique identifier, e.g. species_structure. A species is depicted in the <link target = "ReactDiagView">Reaction Diagram</link> as a green shape.
 	
 	<para>In <def target = "def_RuleBased">rule-based models</def>, molecular details must be specified for all species.  Species are composed of <link target = "Molecules">molecules</link> with bonds that connect
	binding sites. If the molecule has multiple states, each state of the molecule (at each site) must be specified - otherwise the species would represent a pool of different chemical entities and would not be valid. Species with molecular details can be used in any reaction networt.  In rule-based models a species serves as a seed species when
	<def target= "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> models: they are either used as starting set of species to 
	generating a network (using <def target= "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def>), or is used as part of an initial set
	of species for stochastic <def target= "def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> simulations performed using the  
	(using <def target= "def_NFSim">NFSim</def> solver).</para>
 	</introduction>
	<appearance>
	<imgReference target = "Mix_Species.PNG"/>
	<para>The Species Tab has several columns:</para>
	<list> 
		<item>The species <bold>Name</bold>.  New species are automatically named s_number. When a BNGL file is imported species names are automatically generated. 
			The name can be edited in the column.</item> 
		<item>The <def target = "def_structure">structure</def> that contains the species.</item>
		<item><bold>Depiction</bold> depicts the molecular structure of the species. Species without molecular details appear as green shapes. 
			Different molecules comprising a species appear as differently colored shapes, connect by bonds.  
			Sites that have states are marked with a yellow dot. 
			The states of sites are omitted for clarity.</item>
		<item><bold>Links</bold> show links to pathway items (see <link target="PathwayOverview">Biology Pathways</link>); double click on that link to navigate to the Pathway Diagram. 
		A text bubble icon indicates the presence of annotations for the current selection in the <link target ="PP_Annotations">Annotations Properties Pane</link>.</item>
		<item><bold>BioNetGen Definition</bold> provides a BNGL string for species with molecular detail. The two ends of the same bond will have the same color font. This field is cannot be edited but is searchable.</item></list> 
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<bold>Edit</bold> molecular details of species in the 
	<link target = "PP_Species">Species Properties pane</link> in the lower window.
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of species using the Search Box to enter a species name or a structure name.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> species by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.</para>
	<para>If you wish to use <link target = "PathwayOverview"> Pathways Commons</link> data, select the species and use the 
	<link target = "PathLink"> Pathway Links</link> button.</para>
	<para><bold>Add or Edit Annotations</bold> using the <link target= "PP_Annotations">Annotations</link> tab in the Properties Pane.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
