<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Molecules" target="Molecules">

	<introduction>
	<bold>Molecules</bold> are the principal component of rule-based model specification. 
	They are used to create <link target = "Species">Species</link>, 
	define <link target = "ReactionRules"> Reaction Rules</link> and 
	<link target="Observables">Observables</link>. 
	Molecules are structured objects comprised of components (called <bold>sites</bold>) that can
	bind to each other, both within a molecule and between molecules. <bold>Sites</bold> typically
	represent physical parts of proteins, such as the SH2 and SH3 domains of the adapter protein
	Grb2. <bold>Sites</bold> may also be associated with a list of states, 
	intended to represent states or properties of the site, e.g. phosphorylation status  	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	The Molecules Tab displays a table of the Molecule name, Cartoon depiction of each molecule and the 
	<def target = "def_BioNetGen"> BioNetGen </def> molecular definition. In the Cartoon, green circle denotes 
	molecular site, while small yellow circle denotes that this Site has possible states. 
	Selecting molecule brings the <link target = "PP_Molecules">Molecule Properties</link> 
	in the bottom right pane, where a user can specify and edit a selected <bold>Molecule</bold>.
	<imgReference target = "BNG_MoleculesTable.png"> </imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> A molecule can be specified in two ways:
	<list>
	<item>If a user is proficient in BNGL, initial specification can be done as BNGL string, with a user clicking on 
	(Add new here) in the Name column, and then typing or copying BNGL string into BioNetGen definition field. 
	This way of specification is useful when a new Molecule is copied from external BNGL code. 
	Once Enter is pressed, the <bold>Molecule</bold> definition is no more editable in the table.
	</item>
	<item>Alternative way is to enter a name of a Molecule here, and specify it in 
	the <link target = "PP_Molecules">Molecule Properties</link> bottom pane. 
	This is the only way to edit existing molecules, it guarantees that Molecule definition is updated 
	everywhere in the model - in <link target = "Species">Species</link>, 
	 <link target = "ReactionRules"> Reaction Rules</link> and <link target="Observables">Observables</link>.  
	</item>
	</list>
    </para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of species using the Search Box to enter a species name or a structure name.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> molecules by highlighting and using the "Delete" button below the table.
	Molecule will not be deleted if it is used elsewhere in the model.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the molecules within the <link target = "PP_Molecules"> 
	Molecule Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
