<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Observables" target="Observables">

	<introduction>
	The <bold>observables</bold> are used to specify model outputs, which are functions of the
	population levels of multiple chemical species that share a set of properties. For example, if one
	could measure the tyrosine phosphorylation level of a particular protein, then one might be
	interested in determining the total amount of all chemical species containing the phosphorylated
	form of this protein. A function for calculating such a quantity is an <bold>Observable</bold>.
	<bold>Observables</bold> are computed over a set of chemical species that share similar properties. 
	There are two <bold>Observable Types</bold>. 
	<list>
	<item>An observable of the <bold>Molecules
	type</bold> is a weighted sum of the population levels of the chemical species matching the pattern(s)
	in the observable. Each population level is multiplied by the number of times that the species is
	matched by the pattern(s). 
	</item>
	<item>An observable of the <bold>Species type</bold> is simply an unweighted sum of
	the population levels of the matching chemical species. A Molecules type for a dimer will give 
	the number of receptors in receptor dimers. A Species type for a dimer will give the number of 
	receptor dimers.
	</item> 
	</list>	
	</introduction>
	
	<appearance>
	The Observables Tab displays a table of the Observable name, Cartoon depiction of each observable, the 
	<def target = "def_BioNetGen"> BioNetGen </def> definition and Observable's type.   
	Selecting Observable brings the <link target = "PP_Observables">Observable Properties</link> 
	in the bottom right pane, where a user can specify and edit a selected <bold>Observable</bold>. 
	The composition of Observable is the following:
	<list>
	<item>Each Observable consists of one or more <bold>Species Patters</bold> that 
	define common features of species selected by Observable.</item>
	<item>Each SpeciesPattern consists of one or more of Molecules (connected through explicit bonds) 
	with some sites having specified state values. </item>
	<item>Sites that have specified state value are shown in green.</item> 
	<item>Sites that are explicitly bound to another site, 
	declared unbound or bound are shown in green with bond (if exists) shown in solid color.</item>
	<item>Sites than can be in any state and can be bound or unbound are shown in white.</item>
	<item>Sites that have possible multiple states have yellow sign above site shape.</item>
	</list>
	<imgReference target = "BNG_ObservablesTable.png"> </imgReference>
	</appearance>
	
	<operations>
	<para><bold>Edit</bold> An Observable can be specified in two ways:
	<list>
	<item>If a user is proficient in BNGL, initial specification can be done as BNGL string, with a user clicking on 
	(Add new here) in the Name column, and then typing or copying BNGL is copied from external BNGL code. 
	Once Enter is pressed, the <bold>Observable</bold> definition is no more editable in the table.
	</item>
	<item>Alternative way is to enter a name of a Observable here, and specify it in 
	the <link target = "PP_Observables">Observable Properties</link> bottom pane. 
	This is the only way to edit existing Observables, it guarantees that Observable is updated 
	consistently with <link target = "Molecules">Molecules</link> definition.   
	</item>
	</list>
    </para>
	<para> <bold>Filter</bold> the list of species using the Search Box to enter a species name or a structure name.</para>
	<para><bold>Delete</bold> observable by highlighting and using the "Delete Selected" button below the table.</para>
	<para><bold>Add annotation </bold> about the observable within the <link target = "PP_Observables"> 
	Molecule Properties pane </link> in the bottom window.</para>
	</operations>
	
	<properties>
	</properties>

</page>

</vcelldoc>
