<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="How to create a rule-based model" target="RBCreate">

	<introduction> 
There are several ways to create a <def target= "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> model:
	 
<para><bold>Import</bold> an existing rule-based model encoded in BNGL format, using <link target = "ImportBNGL">File->Import menu</link>.
The rule-based model will be created with two applications: a <def target= "def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> application called <bold>NFSim</bold>, and a <def target= "def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> 
network application called <bold>BioNetGen</bold>. 
If some features in a BNGL file are not supported by VCell, a pop-up window appears
with suggestions for correcting unsupported features.
If features in a BNGL file (e.g. specifying a fixed concentration value) are supported by 
<def target= "def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> but not by <def target= "def_NFSim">NFSim</def>, 
only a single deterministic rule-based application will be created.</para>

<para><bold>Create</bold> a new rule-based model or <bold>convert</bold> an existing single-compartment reaction network model into a rule-based model by adding rule-based features using the <link target = "PhysOverview">Physiology</link> tabs.</para>

<para>To create a new rule-based model, the user has to perform the following operations:
<list>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "Molecules">Molecules</link> - structured objects 
with binding sites having optional attribute states</item>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "SpeciesTabView">Species</link> that are made of 
molecules (optionally) connected through binding sites. These composite species will serve as seed species for either
network generation or network-free simulation.</item>
<item>Create one or more <def target = "def_ReactionRules">reaction rules</def> 
(specified in the <link target = "ReactTabView">Reactions</link> Table) that describe transformations 
of species classes by specifying initial and final states of molecules participating in the reaction.</item>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "Observables">Observables</link> that describe classes of species with specified features, 
e.g. having the same site in a phosphorylated state.</item>
</list></para>
	
	</introduction>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>