<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="How to create a rule-based model" target="RBCreate">

	<introduction> 
There are two ways to create a <def target= "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> model:
<list>
<item>Import existing rule-based model encoded in BNGL format, using <link target = "ImportBNGL">File->Import menu</link>.
The rule-based model will be created with two applications: <link target = "NFSimApp">network-free application</link>
called NFSim app, and <link target = "BNGApp">deterministic network application</link> called BioNetGen app.
In some cases, when some features in BNGL file (such as fixed value of concentration) are supported by 
BioNetGen but not NFsim, 
only a single deterministic rule-based application will be created.</item>
<item>Create a new rule-based model using <link target = "PhysOverview">Physiology</link> tabs.</item>
<item>Convert an existing single-compartment reaction network model into rule-based by adding rule-based features.</item>
</list>
To create a new rule-based model, the user has to perform the following operations:
<list>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "Molecules">Molecules</link> that are structured objects 
that have binding sites having optional attribute state</item>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "CompositeSpecies">Composite Species</link> that are made of 
molecules connected through binding sites. These composite species will serve as seed species for either
network generation or network-free simulation.</item>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "Observables">Observables</link> that describe classes of species with specified features, 
e.g. having the same site being phosphorylated.</item>
<item>Create one or more <link target = "ReactionRules">Reaction Rules</link> that describe transformations 
of species classes by specifying of the initial and final states of participating in reaction molecules.</item>
</list>
	</introduction>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>