<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="How to simulate a rule-based model" target="RBCreate">

	<introduction> 
	<para>Once rule-based features are specified in Physiology, a user has mulktiple choices of how to simulate. As standard with 
		Virtual Cell, a Rule-Based BioModel may have numerous 
	Applications, including <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> and 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> (<def target="def_RuleBased">rule-based</def>) applications 
	and special <def target="def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> application.  
	Each Application, in turn can have multiple Simulations, in which different numerical
	methods or conditions are used.</para>
	
	<para><bold>Rule-based Deterministic and Stochastic Applications</bold></para>
	<para>If a user chooses to start <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> or 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> applications, the <def target="def_BioNetGen">BioNetGen</def> network-generation
	algorithm will be used to generate the complete network of species and reactions 
	that is obtained by applying the set of reaction rules to the 
	set of <def target="def_SeedSpecies">seed species</def>. Initial amounts
	of seed species are defined in <link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> specification tab.
	<link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> specification parameters 
	(number of iterations to apply rules and maximal number of molecules per species in generated network) 
	can be used to control the size of the network,
	which otherwise can become infinite. The generated species and reactions can be seen in 
	<link target = "NetworkSpecifications">Network</link> tab, but not added to the 
	<link target = "ReactDiagView">Reaction Diagram</link> view. </para>
	
	<para>After the network is generated, regular determiministic or 
		stochastic <link target = "simulations_overview">simulations</link> can be run.</para>
	
	<para><bold>Network-Free Applications</bold></para>
	<para>If a user chooses to start <def target="def_NetworkFree">network-free</def> applications, 
	no network-generation attempt will be done and the amounts of model <link target = "Observables">Observables</link> 
	and initially defined <link target = "SpeciesTabView">species</link> will be simulated using 
	<def target="def_NFSim">NFSim</def> engine. Simulation parameters can be defined in
	<link target = "NFSimSimulationEditor">NFSim Simulation Editor</link>.</para>
	
	
	<para><bold>Rule-Based MathModel</bold></para>
	MathModel for <def target="def_Deterministic">deterministic</def> or 
	<def target="def_Stochastic">stochastic</def> applications generated for the rule-based model 
	have a standard VCell structure with the full list of species and reactions, observables
	given by functions. MathModel for <def target="def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> application has a new syntax.
	</introduction>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>