<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vcelldoc>
<page title="Introduction to Rule-Based Modeling" target="RuleBasedTheory">

	<introduction>
	A <def target = "def_RuleBased">rule-based</def> model is specified as a set of <def target = "def_ReactionRules">reaction rules</def>, which are
	associated with specific rate laws. Given a set of seed <link target = "SpeciesTabView">species</link>, 
	<def target = "def_ReactionRules">reaction rules</def> identify
	those species that have the features required to undergo the transformation from
	reactants to products specified in the reaction rule. Interactions represented in a
	reaction rule are independent of features not explicitly indicated in the reaction rule. Thus, multiple
	species may qualify as reactants in a set of reactions defined by a single reaction rule.
	
	<para>The modeler can define which components and modifications of a <link target = "Molecules">molecule</link> or
	molecular assembly affect a particular chemical transformation, and which do not.
	Furthermore, the modeler has the ability to account for steric interference, cooperativity,
	and any other factors that might influence the rate of a reaction. A reaction rule can
	state, for example, that “any cell-surface monomeric receptor having an available
	extracellular binding site and any free extracellular ligand can interact and form
	a ligand–receptor complex; the probability of this interaction depends only on
	the total numbers of cell-surface monomeric receptors and extracellular ligands
	and does not depend on the specific state of the receptor cytosolic domain.” In
	this example, we assume that the state of the cytoplasmic domain of the receptor does not affect
	ligand–receptor binding, and thus to parameterize all the reactions specified
	by the ligand–receptor interaction rule requires just two rate constants: on and
	off rates.</para>
	<para> The rule below depicts the EGF receptor with a binding site for egf (l), a second unspecified site (r) and two phosphorylation sites (Y1068 and Y11848) that can be phosphorylated, unphosphorylated, bound or unbound, combining with an EGF molecule with a receptor binding site (r):</para>
	<imgReference target = "rule1.PNG"/>
	<para>Some of the possible reactions generated by this rule are:</para>
	<imgReference target = "reac-combined.PNG"/>
	</introduction>

	<appearance>  
	 
	</appearance>

	<operations>  
	

	</operations>
	
</page>

</vcelldoc>